I'm Noah and I'm Ben and you're listening to Product Journey.
Hey folks, today we got Justin Jackson on the podcast.
He is the co-founder of Transistor, which is a podcasting hosting company.
He's also the founder of Megamaker, a community for founders and of course, avid podcast lover
and listener. Hi Justin. Hey, how's it going? It's nice to be here. Thanks for coming on,
Justin. I listen to the show every week, so it's fun to finally talk to people that you only
hear talking to you. Yes, same actually. Stuck to have you. Yeah, we can kind of finally make this
one by one connection. Now we can just like talk actually together instead of, oh you listen,
then I'll listen. Yeah, totally. It's funny also because I've seen Ben before. We've never talked,
but I had to come up with a vision in my head of what Noah looked like and now I can actually see.
For the rest of the listeners at home, they don't know yet, but now I know. I'm a part of the secret
club. Yeah, was it what you expected? Well, usually I've been podcasting since 2012 and
usually I'm the disappointment when people meet me in person. They go, I thought you would be a
lot taller. Yeah, I feel like that always happens when you hear someone's voice. Like you,
you know, if it's deeper, you kind of, you know, depict a certain kind of person in your mind or
just depend on the voice and then usually it's always not what you're thinking. Yeah, yeah. See,
if I had to guess, I'd guess that Noah is about six feet tall and I'm going to guess Ben is about
the same height as me. I'm five foot eight. How did I do? So you're pretty good. I'm six foot three.
Okay. And I'm trying to calculate centimeters to foot right now. Oh yeah. See, this is the weird
Canadian thing is that we use the metric system, but we are so close to the US that we end up doing
measurements in inches. So I'm almost exactly six foot tall. Oh, you're almost exactly six feet. Okay.
See now, now everybody knows everybody's just adjusted. Maybe we should just, maybe we should
just attach images to the show notes. So photos of us. I think, I think every podcast show notes
needs to have stats on people. Noah, six foot three. Ben. Yeah. 60, how many centimeters is that?
That's one, 185 or 186. 185 centimeters. Yeah. Give people some stats, you know.
That's what they want to hear. Blue eyes, dark, bondage, dirty blonde hair.
Form a picture. So, yeah. So we're glad to have you on the show, Justin. We kind of, two topics
that we're kind of interested in that I know you talk a decent amount about is like audience building
and like your market and starting with a market instead of an idea. So we kind of wanted to jump
into both those two topics and just kind of dig deeper into that. Perfect. So yeah. It's like my
favorite thing to talk about right now. Yeah. I think some people are getting sick of me talking
about it, but I just can't stop thinking about it. So it's what naturally kind of comes out.
And actually I had, we had a question about that kind of like with building an audience. That was
one of the things we're interested in. Like, do you ever feel like you run out of new things to say?
I mean, one thing that's been helpful for me is that since 2013, we've had this online community
with Mega Maker. And so people are interacting and asking questions all the time. And those discussions
often inspire my thinking of, oh, wait a second. It's actually, like a lot of my tweets come out
of conversations that I've had inside of Mega Maker or things I'm listening to on a podcast
or even things I've read in a book. I'm reading something and it brings up these thoughts. And
I treat Twitter kind of like the local comedy club, where you go and test out material.
It's like, okay, I'm going to try this out and see how it lands. And it's also just a helpful way for
me to process my thinking. So no, I haven't run out of things to talk about yet. I do have moments
like John and I are doing our podcast now. And I think we're ready for the year to be done in some
ways, ready for things to kind of wind down. And so I think there's such thing as fatigue
when you're publishing something every week and you eventually need to give your brain space to
just explore other things and have other ideas. But yeah, most of the time, as long as I'm
interacting with people and real life situations and also doing experiments in my own life,
I haven't run out of anything to say yet. Yeah, I could see the fatigue in that you feel like
you have to have something to say, at least every week when you have the podcast. You have to have
a new thing that you're thinking about or that you can dive into. Yeah, we've definitely kind
of seen that. Yeah, and I think this is what that's why breaks are important. I almost get this more
with because podcasting, you can just turn on the mics and if you have a rough idea of where you
want to go, you can talk it out. But writing, I find, is a lot more takes a lot more of my energy.
And so writing that weekly newsletter that I write is, there are definitely weeks where that is tough.
Not because I don't have an idea, but sometimes to process ideas and actually
write it in a way that makes sense is hard. But yeah, in either case, breaks are good.
I can only say I'm receiving that newsletter and you're doing pretty good, I guess.
Yes, I'm enjoying it.
That almost gives me more pressure because then I'm like, oh, people like it. I got to keep going.
Yeah, well in that case, I hated it.
So we got a couple of questions about audience and I think I have a pretty interesting one.
That is, what makes a good audience and do you think that you should like,
do you think you have to be part of your audience? Do you have to feel comfortable among the people?
So I've actually changed my tune a little bit on this. I think now if you're starting a business,
the market is the most important thing, the market you choose. And when I say market,
I don't mean market as in just a identifiable group of people. I'm talking about a group of people
that buys X. So the diamond market last year was $4.5 billion or something like that. To me,
that's a market. It's a market where you can see people in motion, preferably buying something,
but sometimes it's just people in motion doing something. And everything kind of hinges on that,
which market you are in. So as an example, Taylor Otwell is the founder of Laravel,
which is the most popular PHP programming framework in the world. He has a huge audience.
If you look at his audience, quote unquote, on Twitter, he's got, I don't know, hundreds of
thousands of followers. Let's just check because I don't want people to be. So well, he has,
okay, he has 82,000 followers on Twitter. So for a lot of people, that would be a big audience.
Mm hmm. And if you go to LaraCon, you see he's got 800 people in the audience, right?
And he has tons of people buying his stuff. He has millions of people using Laravel.
But all of that is in the context of a bigger market. It's hard to count the number of
programmers in the world, but let's just say a reasonable estimate is that there's 5 million
PHP programmers in the world. Would you agree with that, Ben?
Yeah, definitely. I've actually used Laravel for a couple of projects.
Okay, there you go. And so 5 million PHP programmers in the world. And let's just take
one element of that market, not including all the tools they buy, not including everything else that
you need to be a programmer. Let's just think about salary. And these are just guesses, but
let's say on average, an average PHP programmer in the world makes $25,000 a year. Well, 25,000
times 5 million is 125 billion, I think. That's $125 billion being spent on salaries for PHP
developers alone. That's a massive market. It's not just a big group of people, but it's also a
big group of people where there's some sort of economic activity being generated. And
I think it's why products in the Laravel community often have a magnified
impact compared to other things. So I have a course called Marketing for Developers that did
pretty good. But if you take all of the developers in the world and then you ask how many of those
developers want to learn marketing, it's a much smaller slice. How many developers in the world
are PHP developers that want to make their jobs better? Well, that's probably 5 million.
Mm-hmm. And so you can compare results and you can see that kind of everything hinges on the market.
How big the market is, how big your audience can be within that market. And then all the multiples
all kind of depend on that. So how much money is being spent in that market already and how much
of that can you carve off for yourself? You know, Taylor, presumably, he's only carved off a little
bit of the PHP market. Like there's still other frameworks. There's still programmers that don't
know or use about, sorry, don't know about or use Laravel. So he's still got plenty of room to grow
as well. But even then, like Taylor Ottwell as a solo person has sold $10 million worth of software
to PHP developers. That's pretty crazy. That's insane. And he just recently took on employees.
So, you know, there's funded startups in San Francisco right now that have millions of dollars
in funding. Staff of 50 people and they haven't sold $10 million worth of software.
I think the market that you're in determines everything. And when you have
what Corey Gwynn calls demonstrated demand, so you can actually see the demand,
that's kind of what you're looking for. You're looking for people in motion.
A large group of people in motion who are where there's economic activity being generated from
whatever they're doing. So yeah, so you would basically say start out with the market, try to
find a market you want to work in and then start building an audience around that. Like don't worry
as much about do you feel comfortable in that audience or yeah, those kind of things. I mean,
I mean, this is where it gets tricky. This is why business is so hard because you have to,
you apply all of these filters to get to where you want to go. So it's like, it's not enough
to just be in a good market. You actually have to be interested in that market.
You have to have good founder market fit. You have to, you know, you have to then be able to
identify some sort of need in that market. You have to, then you have to actually
execute on some things and, you know, make some sort of connection. I don't think you have to
necessarily build an audience, but you get a lot of leverage from who you know and who knows you.
Who you know is just making connections. We're making connections right now. Now the three of
us know each other and even the fact that we've been on a phone call makes it a lot easier for me
to ask a favor of you in the future or for you to ask a favor of me. That's networking. That's who
you know. Who knows you is the audience effect and that, I mean, that could be very helpful.
There are people who have built businesses without doing that. Ruben Gámez is a good example
of someone who's just built a software business almost purely on search engine results and
optimizing search engine results. I think it's one of the levers you can use. I think without
any sort of human connection, it's very difficult. You do have to connect with other people.
You do have to connect with other human beings and again this is why it's helpful to be interested
in the market you're in. Sometimes even that can be enough. I'm really interested in the Laravel
community. I'm not really a Laravel developer, but I've spoken at their conference three times.
I really like the people and I would say I'm part of the community even though I'm not a power user
of Laravel. There has to be something that draws you to that market. There has to be something that
keeps you there and you're probably going to need some sort of connection with some key people in
that market to make it work. How you get there is kind of the individual journey. I'm almost 40 now
and it's very difficult to say what are the 10 steps that brought you to Transistor because
it's layer on layer on layer of my life going back to when I was a kid. All of those steps
up till now lead me to where I'm at now. I think you can optimize for some of those things. Where
you point yourself in life has a big determination of where you'll end up. I think the connections
you make matter a lot. I think what you put out into the world matters a lot. Podcasting, blogging,
public speaking, but even just anything not open source projects. Anything you put out into the
world can help. In terms of adding all those up and going, okay, what really matters? A lot harder
to figure that out. I think that's a pretty interesting point because when we started out
with a podcast, I think we were both on the track of we should build an audience.
It's kind of like we're shifting away from that a little bit. I recently came across this tweet from
Jane Portman and Rob Walling, Jane Portman from Usalist, who were also talking about that, how
they didn't really need an audience. It just fits very well to what you just said, I guess.
There's one more thing that I would like to get your opinion on because you're probably
familiar with Derek Reimer and what happened with Level. Do you feel like having an audience
might not always be not necessary, but also maybe lead to false positives?
Oh, definitely. Yeah. Again, it can be really helpful too. To say that
my audience didn't help in launching Transistor would be disingenuous. It definitely helps. It
still helps. But there is a risk because what you're looking for is you're looking for some
sort of momentum. When you launch something, you're trying to gauge what kind of response
is this getting. When Apple releases the new iPhone, how many people are lined up outside
of the Apple store? Apple actually can fall prey to this because they've got all these
mega fans that are going to line up day one no matter what. You could see these huge lineups
and you could go, oh wow, the new iPhone is a big success. But unless the rest of the world
shows up, then it's not going to be a success. Yeah, that's a pretty good analogy.
Lineups on day one, they are helpful, but they can also,
like I've launched things, I think still to this day my best launch ever
was for this online series on product marketing. The first couple weeks, tons of people showed up.
When I started asking them, what are you hoping to achieve out of this? What brought you here?
They said, oh, I'm just a big fan. I just get everything that you put out. That's nice, but
it became really clear in the coming months that no one else cared. That's the disadvantage of
having an audience. When people are really invested in your journey, they're going to show up no
matter what. They're going to show up just because they have a personal connection to you.
But ultimately, if you're going to run a business, you need people who are going to show up,
and then more people are going to show up, and then more people are going to show up.
This is actually why I think the market you choose matters so much. I've gotten into
some public disagreements with people who could be right. These are my friends and people I respect.
The idea of going after a small niche, I think—again, maybe people are—I don't know.
The idea of going after a small niche is just you're limiting yourself to, let's say, a pool of
5,000, 10,000 people. That's like going to a little tiny stream and trying to scoop up a little bit
of water from a tiny stream, as opposed to going after a big, massive market in motion. That's
going to a rushing river and just putting your cup in the river and just scooping out. Sure,
you might be able to fill up your cup at a small little stream, but the rushing river has so much
water that it's a lot easier for a solo bootstrapper to just put their cup in the
river and then scoop up a bunch of water. I think sometimes this idea of niche
leads people to the wrong places. They're just looking for these tiny streams that no one else
has ever discovered before. They say, well, we've got to avoid the big rivers because everyone knows
about those. Yeah, but it's a lot easier to get your cup in a big river and scoop out some water
than to find this tiny little thing that nobody knows exists. Yeah, and in the end, your cup is
bigger than the river. Exactly. I wonder if where the kind of disagreement that you have with people
about that idea really just comes from the end goal with what people want to do with their business.
Basically, where I hear what you're saying, I guess the opposite of what you say in that find a
niche market, the advice that I have typically seen that from is places like Y Combinator or
startups that are really trying to do a go big or go home kind of business. I think a good example
is Peter Thiel, the co-founder of PayPal, his book Zero to One. I don't know if you've heard of that or
read it, but that's almost his whole thing is basically go for the new markets. That's where
you can make, really, there's a lot of opportunity to make a huge business and that's kind of like
what PayPal, Facebook, some of those giant companies now did. Well, so yeah, if people
that are saying that kind of advice are venture capitalists or people that that's their goal,
then I could see that making sense. But for bootstrappers, I think that is then very dangerous.
So maybe, I don't know, I'm just wondering maybe that's where the disconnect is
between those different ideas. Yeah, I think part of it is probably semantics
and part of it is this is all really emotional stuff because the way that you are currently doing
your thing kind of informs your bias. The way that you've achieved success in the past informs
your bias. I mean, I said things at 20 years old that I don't believe anymore. I said things at 30
years old that I don't believe anymore. And so a lot of this is just where we're at and what's
working for us right now. And I mean, I was on Twitter, this guy, Evan Golden was saying,
you can stretch the definition pretty wide. It's always easy to justify,
people are spending money. What did he say? He said, people are spending money on tacos everywhere.
This could justify me in opening a taco stand featuring dirt flavored tacos.
There's lots of evidence people want tacos. Evan's a friend of mine, but these are the kind of
arguments I get into on Twitter. But I think that unfortunately, that's exactly what I do want to do
is I want to say, is there any evidence in this market of prior of demonstrated demand? That's
just a great word from Corey Gwynn. And so PayPal, let's take PayPal as an example.
What was the market for what PayPal was doing before PayPal existed? What was massive?
The Western Union, like bank transfer, like money transfer market, people trying to pay for things
with credit cards online, but having to go through their credit card processors. There's all sorts of
friction, but there's tons of evidence that there was billions of dollars being spent in that
market already. And so it's not like PayPal invented anything. I mean, sure, they created
a new way of doing those things, but they didn't create the market. They were riding a wave that
already existed. They just saw the wave coming and they built a better surfboard that enabled them
to ride further than anyone else had at the time. And this is what I'm talking about is really,
in some ways, what Evan is saying is like, I'm stretching the definition to say,
is there any sort of prior or existing demonstrated demand for this thing?
And I think you could see that in almost every major product launch.
Like the iPhone, before the iPhone was the Blackberry and the Palm, and you can keep going
back and back and back, right? There's a demonstrated demand for these things. Even if you look at,
I can remember as a kid looking in catalogs wanting to buy a portable television,
right? From Radio Shack or whatever. There was demand for portable televisions that were battery
operated. They never worked very well, but there was demonstrated demand for that thing. Well,
a big part of the iPhone is just a portable television. And I think that's the reason why
just a portable television, right? At least that's how my kids use it. It's like Netflix all day long.
Yeah, definitely now. So I think the point is to look for some sort of demonstrated demand
and to think, is this a market in motion? Is there evidence that people are doing something
about this right now? So, yeah. Yeah, so the market is kind of being defined as
like a problem to be solved or like a job to be done rather than, I don't know, maybe how like
marketers sometimes think about markets as almost, I feel like they can kind of put it into a box of
like a specific solution or a specific area in that way. So yeah, really focusing from what you're
saying, it sounds like, yeah, really focusing on the problem that needs to be solved. Is that a big
market of people want that? Yeah. Yeah. Yeah. Yes. Exactly. That's exactly what I'm talking about.
There's lots. You can see this with, if you go into product hunt and you find,
I run into this all the time, products that are no longer around. There's all these like dead startups.
Oh yeah. And in almost every case, there just wasn't enough demonstrated demand for that thing.
They were good ideas. They kind of made sense logically. But if you looked at it and go,
okay, but who's doing something about this right now? That's really what's most interesting about
Derek Reimer's story is that once he started talking to the people on his waiting list and
asking, okay, well, what are you doing about this problem right now? And often their response was,
well, nothing. We haven't done anything. You haven't searched on Google for an answer? No.
You haven't searched the Slack extension store? No. Well, that's a bad sign. If people aren't even
willing to do something free, which is just search for a solution, how are you going to
convince them to jump over all of these hurdles and actually take out their credit card out of
their wallet and pay you for something? And this is another thing I've maybe had a hard time to
articulate is it takes so much momentum to get someone to take out their credit card
that you've got to be sure that what you're proposing is something that they really,
really want. And really the only way to figure that out, the only way to see that clearly is,
are they doing something about it right now? And is there enough of these people on mass doing this,
doing something about it right now? Yeah, I love that piece of advice. I actually thought that it's,
I think it was actually you who said that you should go to Twitter and just search,
search if people are typing something like, I don't know, maybe even using their grammar example,
search in Twitter for switching away from Slack or switch away from Slack and see how many results
you actually find. And there are a couple I did that for fun. But yeah. And I mean, that's just
step one, right? Because it's pretty low friction to tweet your disappointment with something. But
at least that's something. And then you would actually want to talk with folks and ask them
questions like, okay, well, what caused you to switch? How long did you think about switching
before it happened? What did you have to do internally in your team to make that switch happen?
And that's where you're going to get a lot of answers. It's one reason I worked for a
project management software startup. And what I didn't know before I joined is how hard it is
to get people to switch project management software. And it's remarkably difficult because
everybody has an opinion on the team, right? The developers want one thing,
the marketing folks want one another thing, the CTO wants one thing, like it goes around and around.
And so you have to convince not just one person, but 10, 20 people to make this decision.
And then the other kind of bad sign. So despite how difficult it is to get people to switch,
people do switch all the time. And that's also a bad sign because they don't just switch once,
and then they're satisfied. They switch, they try Trello, and then they're like, no, this didn't work.
And then they try Basecamp, and then like, oh, that doesn't work. And then they try Jira.
They all end up in Jira, right? That's how it works. And so when you actually get into those
real discussions with people about what does the actual process look like, even a market like
project management, it has its own minefield, right? Like there's pros and cons. And I think
for bootstrappers, it's a lot harder. It's why we've seen, you know, Basecamp got in early,
and so they've done okay. But really, besides Basecamp, everybody else is venture funded
because it just costs so much money. And if you get on their list, like people, Jira will call you.
They've got salespeople that want to onboard you, right? Because they know the only way to push this
through the whole funnel is to have a lot of kind of concerted effort doing it. So a lot of these
things, a lot of these decisions depend on whether or not you're bootstrapping, whether or not you're
bootstrapping as a solo founder, because some of these ideas and markets are just harder to reach
as a bootstrapper or solo founder. Right. So with that in mind, and you know, starting with the
market, I guess, and maybe some ways what sounds like what you'd say is basically start with the
market filter. Like that's the first filter that you want to put on of how to basically choose
what problem you're going to solve, how you're going to do it. How do you,
like it seems like, you know, you start talking to customers, start talking to users,
it takes a while before you can really know what's the right approach, what's the right solution to
actually build. What do you do if that solution ends up being something that isn't something that
a bootstrapper can do? Or maybe it's a solution that doesn't use your strengths, you know, as a
founder, it doesn't use your skills, your abilities. So how do you handle that when, I guess,
starting with a market? Because, yeah, I mean, I guess in some ways it kind of goes back to there's
just all these filters and in some ways all these things have to align, which is obviously very hard.
Yeah, I mean, I think that's just the, this is another unpopular tweet of mine, but it is just,
and I had to admit this before I had any success, but what you kind of have to admit in some way,
on one side is we're not all going to make it. And a lot of people don't like hearing that,
but we're not all going to make it. There's no way that every single aspiring entrepreneur in the
world can apply all of these filters and come out on the other side. And by the way, even you come
out on the other side and, you know, like I have a business now that's doing pretty well,
it could disappear tomorrow. Every day I wake up going, well, maybe today's the day it disappears,
right? Because markets change and they can change really fast. And so there's no,
like there's nothing really romantic about starting a business. It's just,
there's all sorts of things that have to align for it to work. And a lot of us aren't going to make it.
So you have to hold that on one side. Well, at the same time on the other side, these things are
intention. On the other side, you have to be super optimistic that you're going to make it
and that you're just going to keep trying because the other thing I've seen anecdotally, I don't
know if this is scientific, but the people who keep trying, who keep working at it, who keep pushing
that ball forward, many of them do make it. And so there's a little bit of how long can you last,
how long can you try? It's why a lot of successful entrepreneurs actually tend to be statistically
older because by that point in your life, you've had a bunch of industry experience. So you know
what an industry is, you know, you've got connections in that industry, you've seen the
pain points, you've seen how they spend money, you know, there's all of this accrued experience
that ends up being helpful. And, you know, time is kind of what allows you to keep pushing, right?
So it's not saying you shouldn't try in your 20s, but because you could, it could all align, right?
My friend Nathan Barry is not even 30 yet and has already achieved more as a founder than a lot of
folks. But I think you have to have this idea of, well, it might not happen, but I'm going to try,
and this might be a 10-year project or this might be a 20-year project. And you almost have to be
okay with that. Like, this just might take time for everything to align. And the whole time I'm
going to have to be working as if this will eventually work out. And not just doing the
same thing, putting yourself in new circles, getting outside of your comfort zone. I've
described this before as, is it Command and Conquer that uses Fog of War where you're just on a map
and everything's dark and you're exploring it? So if you think about that as a metaphor, like,
when you start out, you're just in that map and all you can see is around you, right? And as you
explore more of the map, more and more parts become illuminated. And every once in a while,
you'll end up in a spot of the map where things just happen, right? Like, you get a bunch of
bounty or you run into a bunch of enemies or whatever. And it's kind of like that. Like,
you're walking around. For me, for example, I was walking around and I just happened to
run into Adam Wathen, who I had no idea who he was or anything about him. But he ended up being
quite an influential person in the Laravel community. And that was just me wandering
around the map and him wandering around the map too. And then I was meeting each other. And once
I could see, like, I've learned tons about a lot of my thoughts about, like, choosing a market first
have been because of the influence of the Laravel community and looking at Taylor and Adam Wathen
and Steve Shoger and Jeffrey Way build these crazy businesses. Because in my little world,
before I met them, you know, this is the way things were done. People like us do things like this.
And then I got over into that area of the map and it was like this whole new world opened up
that I'd never seen before. And without that world opening up, I don't think I would have.
Well, I don't think a lot of things would have happened. And so there's
clearly you have to kind of be always doing things, trying things, getting out of your comfort zone,
meeting new people. And I think the advice I would give my kids is just to explore as much
of the map as you can, as early as you can. Because the more exploration you do, I think I
stayed too local too long. You know, I grew up in a small little farming town in Alberta.
And then the big city was Edmonton. And I just spent too much time there. And then, you know,
like the first time I flew into New York, I was like, holy shit, like, there's a lot of people
here. There's a lot of money here. There's a lot of businesses here that I've never even
imagined before. And it kind of expanded my whole worldview. And unless you're doing that work to
kind of walk around the map and discover new areas. Yeah, I think it'll be harder to,
you know, to find those markets, to find those ideas.
Yeah. So I want to go back a little bit to something you said, you know, kind of talking about how
basically this might not work for all of us. And it's very hard. And yeah, we all might not
make it through. And that's just kind of the truth of it. So like, how do you and I'm just
curious about your situation. Like, how do you go to your wife with that and get her on board for
this whole journey of what we're trying to do? Because that's I'm just curious because that's
definitely something I know me and my wife struggle with a lot just with my last thing. And like,
it is hard. So it's like it's, you know, you it's not just you going on this journey. You're
bringing your whole family with you. Yeah. I mean, again, you probably don't want to look
at the statistics. The statistics are pretty bad. Just don't look. So this podcast has to be titled
Unpopular Opinions with Jackson Jackson. I mean, it's just like if you want the reality,
the reality is not good statistically. I mean, clearly, I think I think all entrepreneurs have
this feeling that maybe they can do it better than the next guy. And because statistically,
you know, millions of people start businesses, but those people are in all sorts of different places,
have all sorts of different leverage, have all sorts of different privilege. You know, there's
there's all these factors that go into, you know, why a person becomes a success or not.
And I think every entrepreneur feels like they've got some secret sauce that'll make them better
than the next guy. Oh, yeah. But I mean, in my early 20s, I started a couple retail shops
that ended up losing a lot of money, and that was hard to recover from as a family.
And so that that is just part of it. Like if you're going to be on that. So that was
almost 20 years ago. And yeah, so now I'm at a place where, you know, maybe I've learned enough
lessons and I've made enough connections that things are happening. But that's a long journey.
That's 10, 20 years of of work. And so. Yeah, I mean, I think that's something you got to consider
with kind of with everything. I don't think you should kill yourself in the process. I think
I think I worked probably too hard a lot of those years when I didn't need to. It's just
wasted cycles trying to make something happen. You know, you're it's far better for you to
book a ticket to a conference that you've never been to than to work 60, 70, 80 hours a week.
Because at least for me, the biggest jumps forward have been because I met somebody outside of my
circle. I met John Buddha, my co-founder, in 2014 at this kind of experimental technology art
design festival called XOXO. And, you know, I wasn't going to go initially. I had to kind
of push myself to get out of the house and actually go. So yeah, I don't think there's any easy answers
there. I think you can stair step your way up. You can do something small on the side and then
see if that evolves into something bigger and then something bigger and then something bigger.
Nathan Barry just wrote a piece on this that I don't fully like or agree with, but maybe I
don't like it just because it's the hard truth. He talks about a series of ladders and, you know,
the first ladder is just like trading time for money and then you kind of work up that ladder,
right? You can work yourself up from making minimum wage up to making more money per hour.
But then you go to the next ladder, which has higher earning potential, but it's harder. It's
just like, okay, now you've got to you're trading time for money, but it's more on your terms,
like consulting. And so then you work your way up that level. And then there's another ladder.
And, you know, these keep going and the difficulty with each ladder goes up. And
but your potential, in his case, he's just talking about income earning potential,
your income earning potential goes up as well. And it is a little bit of a
stair step, right? Like you're moving your way up here and then you're like, oh, well,
there's opportunity over here. So then you might take a few steps back to start here and then
build yourself up here. And then you look at the next ladder, you go, there's more opportunity
over there. So then you go back down and then work your way up. Yeah, that's all possible.
Definitely helps if you have in terms of like having a decent life. It helps if you have a
lot more cash saved up. The more cash you have saved up, the less stress you have.
But that's not always possible either. Right. So that the only way I can think of to alleviate
the stress is to have very low cost of living and or a lot of money saved up.
Yeah.
Money that you can risk that you wouldn't feel bad about losing.
So and you can even hear this in John and I's podcast, you know,
he was working for Cards Against Humanity when we started this. And he also had more money saved
up than I did. And so my stress level when we weren't quite yet full time yet was a lot higher.
I'm just like, oh, God, like, do we got to take investment? Do we got to try to add three or four
more things on top of this to make this work? You can see how desperation affects your actions.
And a lot of businesses you'll see do this. Like one thing's not working quite enough. So then they
add another thing to hopefully bring up more income. And that's not quite bringing enough.
So they add another thing and they just keep adding more and more stuff and more and more
stress to their lives. But yeah, for John, it's easy. He's got no dependence and his cost of
living is low. And he had a bunch of money saved up for him. This isn't as this isn't making or
break it. It's like, no, I can just if this doesn't work. Yeah, I'm fine. So that if you want to make
it easier, I think lower your expenses and save a bunch of money or get someone to give you a bunch
of money or rob a bank or whatever. That goes easier out. I mean, this is why privilege plays
such a big part in business. Like some people do. They get they get a they have a big trust fund and
they get a bunch of money. It does help. Yeah, I agree. Yeah. Yeah, that makes sense.
So maybe as a last question we could end with, maybe you've heard the How I Built This podcast.
They always end with an interesting question, which is so for you, I'm just interested in hearing as
well, like with Transistor, like where you guys gotten so far, how much do you think of that was
luck and how much of it was, you know, you and John's skill and talents and hard work?
It's definitely the accumulation of a lifetime of experience. And I think I think your attitude
matters a lot in that. Right. Like, are you going to keep going out and trying things? Are you going
to keep going out and trying to push the envelope? Are you going to keep going out and put things out
in public? Are you going to go out and meet people? Like if if if you were going to split
test my life and you put one Justin in his room and he never leaves and all he does is play Sonic
the Hedgehog forever. And then you have another version where he's like always going out and
trying to figure things out and trying to build things and trying to write and trying to meet this
person. And for sure, in that A B test, you know, Justin B wins. There's I don't think it's that's
a it's not too difficult to see that. So yeah, there's a lot of luck in where I was born. And
the the the influence of luck starts to go down a lot. Like the the the influence of blind luck,
like just like where you were born, like what what year and country and location and parents
you were born to. After that part, you make your most of your luck just by whatever attitude you
have every day. There's still some privilege that comes with where you were born, but most of that
kind of built in luck is already happened by the time you were born.
Yeah. Cool. Well, thanks, Justin, for coming on. That was a good conversation. Very helpful for
both of us. And I'm sure for our listeners as well. I didn't bum you out too much.
I mean, sometimes you need a little of that gets you back back to the truth.
So, yeah, thanks, Justin, and we'll see you guys in another episode.
And we'll put everything in the show notes. All right. Bye. See you.