Noah: I am Noah.
And I'm Ben, and you're
listening to Product Journey.
Ben: Hey folks.
Today we got Justin
Jackson on the podcast.
He is the co-founder of
Transistor, which is a
podcasting hosting company.
Um, he's also the founder of
MegaMaker, a community for
founders, and of course, AVID
podcast lover and listener.
Hi, Justin.
Justin: Hey, how's it going?
It's nice to be here.
Thanks for coming on, Justin.
I listen to the show every week, so
it's, it's fun to finally Awesome.
Talk to people that you
only hear talking to you.
Yes, same actually.
Yeah.
Ben: Stuck to have you.
Noah: Yeah.
We can kind of finally make
this one by one, uh, connection.
Now we can just like talk
actually together instead of Oh,
you listen, then I'll listen.
Justin: Yeah, totally, totally.
It's funny also because, uh,
I've, I've seen Ben before.
We've never talked, but I had to,
I had to come up with a vision
in my head of what Noah looked
like, and now, now I can actually
see for the rest of the listeners
at home, they, they can't, they
don't know yet, but now I know
I'm a part of the super club.
Noah: Yeah.
Was it what you expected?
Justin: Well, usually.
I've been podcasting since 2012
and usually I'm the disappointment
when people meet me in, in
person, they go, I thought
you would be a lot taller.
Noah: Yeah.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah.
See, I feel like that always
happens when you, you hear
someone's voice like you, you
know, if it's deeper, you kind of.
You know, depict a certain kind
of person in your mind, or if
it's, yeah, it just depend on
the voice and then usually it's
always not what you're thinking.
Yeah.
Justin: Yeah.
See, if I had to guess, I'd
guess that Noah is about six feet
tall, and I'm gonna guess Ben
is about the same height as me.
I'm five foot eight.
How did I do?
Noah: So you're pretty good.
I'm six foot three.
Okay.
Ben: And I'm trying to calculate
centimeters to foot right now.
Justin: Oh, yeah.
I should see, this is the weird
Canadian thing, is that we use
the metric system, but we are so
close to the US that we end up
doing measurements and inches.
So
Ben: I'm almost
exactly six foot tall.
Justin: Oh, you're
almost exactly six feet.
Okay.
See, see now.
Now everybody knows.
Everybody's just adjusted.
You their mind.
Ben: Maybe you should just, maybe
you should just attach, uh, images
to the show notes of photos of us.
Justin: I think.
I think every podcast show notes
needs to have stats on, uh, people.
Noah, six foot three.
Ben.
Yeah.
60.
How many centimeters is that?
That's
Ben: one, uh, 180 5 or 180
Justin: 6.
180 5 centimeters.
Yeah.
Give people some stats.
You know, that's what they
wanna
Noah: hear.
Dark bondish, dirty, blonde hair.
Mm-hmm.
Form a picture.
So, uh, yeah.
So we're glad to have
you on the show, Justin.
Uh, we kind of two topics that
we're kind of interested in that
I know you talk a decent amount
about is like audience building
and like your market and starting
with a market instead of an idea.
Mm-hmm.
So we kind of wanted to jump into.
Both those two topics and just
kind of dig deeper, um, into that.
So, perfect.
Justin: It's like my favorite thing
thing to talk about right now.
Yeah.
That's good.
I think some people are
getting sick of me talking
about it, but I, I just
can't stop thinking about it.
So it's, it's what
naturally kind of comes out.
Noah: And actually I had, we
had a question about that.
Um, kind of like with
building an audience.
Mm-hmm.
That was one of the things
we were interested in, like.
Do you ever feel like you
run out of new things to say?
Justin: Um, I mean, one thing
that's been helpful for me is
that since 2013, we've had this
online community with Mega Maker
and so people are interacting and
asking questions all the time.
And those discussions often inspire
my thinking of, oh, wait a second.
It's actually, I.
Like, a lot of my tweets come out
of conversations that I've had
inside of MegaMaker, or things
I'm listening to on a podcast.
Um, or even things
I've read in a book.
You know, I'm, I'm reading
something and it, it
brings up these thoughts.
And I treat Twitter kind of
like, uh, kind of like the local
comedy club, you know, where
you go and test out material.
It's like, okay, I'm, I'm gonna
try this out and see how it.
How it lands.
And, um, it's also just
a, a helpful way for me
to process my thinking.
So no, I, I, I haven't run
outta things to talk about yet.
I do, I do have moments like John
and I are doing our podcast now,
and I think we're ready for the
year to be done in some ways.
You know, like ready for
things to kind of wind down.
Uh, and so I think there's
such thing as fatigue.
Mm-hmm.
When you're publishing something
every week and you eventually
need to give your brain space
to just explore, you know, other
things and have other ideas.
But yeah, not most of the time,
as long as I'm interacting with
people and real life situations
and also doing experiments in
my own life, I don't, I haven't
run out of anything to say yet.
Noah: Yeah, I could see
the fatigue in that.
Like, you feel like you're, you
have to have something to say like,
at least every week when you have
the podcast, like you have to have
a new thing that you're thinking
about or that you can dive into.
Mm-hmm.
Yeah.
Justin: We've definitely
kind of seen that.
Yeah.
And I, I think this is what,
that's why breaks are important.
Uh, I, I almost get this
more with 'cause podcasting.
You can just turn on the mics and
if you have a rough idea of where
you wanna go, you can talk it out.
But writing I find is a lot more,
uh, takes a lot more of my energy.
And so like writing that
weekly newsletter that I
write is, there are definitely
weeks where that is tough.
I, I not because I don't have an
idea, but sometimes to process
ideas and actually write it in
a way that makes sense is hard.
Um, but yeah, the.
Uh, in either case,
breaks are good.
Ben: I can always say I'm
receiving that newsletter.
And you're doing
pretty good, I guess.
Justin: Well, thanks.
At least I'm enjoying it.
That that almost gives
me more pressure.
'cause then I'm like,
oh, most people like it.
I gotta keep going.
Yeah.
Well when
Noah: that came down, now
Ben: that case I hated it
Justin: every time.
Um,
Ben: So we got a, we got a
couple of questions about
audience and, um, mm-hmm.
I have a, I think I have
a pretty interesting one.
Um, that is what, what makes a good
audience, and do you think that you
should, like, do you think you, you
have to be part of your audience?
Like, um, do, do you have to feel
comfortable among the people?
Justin: Hmm.
So I'm ac I've actually changed
my tune a little bit on this.
Hmm.
I think now if you're starting
a business, Uh, the market
is the most important thing,
the market you choose.
And when I say market, I
don't mean market as in just a
identifiable group of people.
I'm talking about a group
of people that, uh, buys X.
So the diamond market.
Last year was 4.5 billion
or something like that.
To me, that's a market.
It's a market where you can
see people in motion, uh,
preferably buying something,
but sometimes it's just people
in motion doing something and
everything kind of hinges on
that which market you are in.
So, as an example, Taylor Twell
is the founder of Laravel,
which is the most popular p h p
programming framework in the world.
Uh, he has a huge audience.
If you look at his audience,
quote unquote on Twitter,
he's got, I dunno, hundreds of
thousands of, yeah, that's a lot.
Followers.
Let's, let's just check, because
I don't want people to be thought.
Well, uh, he has, okay.
He has 82,000 followers on Twitter.
So for a lot of people that
would be a big audience.
Mm-hmm.
And if you go to Lar
Con, you see he's got 800
people in the audience.
Right.
And he has, you know, tons
of people buying his stuff.
He has millions of
people using Laravel.
But all of that is in the
context of a bigger market.
There's, it's hard to count the
number of programmers in the world,
but let's just say a reasonable
estimate is that there's 5 million.
P h p programmers in the world.
Mm-hmm.
Um, would you agree with that, Ben?
Yeah,
Ben: definitely.
Okay.
I've actually, you know,
I've actually used for
a couple of projects.
Justin: Okay.
There you go.
And so, um, 5 million p h
p programmers in the world.
And let's just say, let's just
take one element of that market.
Not including all the tools
they buy, not including, you
know, everything else that
you need to be a programmer.
Let's just think about salary.
And these are, these are just
guesses, but let's say on average,
an average P H P programmer in
the world makes $25,000 a year.
Well, 25,000 times 5 million
is 125 billion I think.
That's $125 billion being
spent on salaries for
P H P developers alone.
That's a massive market.
It's not just a big group of
people, but it's also a big
group of people who, where
there's some sort of economic
activity being generated.
And, uh, I think it's why products
in the Laravel community often
have a magnified, um, Impact
compared to other things.
So, you know, I have a
course called Marketing for
Developers that did pretty good.
Mm-hmm.
But that's like if you take all
of the developers in the world
and then you ask how many of those
developers wanna learn marketing,
it's a much s smaller slice.
Right.
Yeah.
How many developers in the world
are p h P developers that want,
uh, to make their jobs better?
Well, that's probably 5 million.
Mm-hmm.
And so, You, you can compare
results and you can see that
kind of everything hinges on the
market, how big the market is,
uh, how big the, your audience
can be within that market.
Uh, and then all the multiples
all kind of depend on that.
So how much money is being
spent in that market already,
and how much of that can
you carve off for yourself?
Um, you know, Taylor presumably.
He's only carved off a little
bit of the P H P market.
Like there's still other
frameworks, there's still
programmers that don't know or
use about, sorry, don't know about
or use Laravel, so he's still got
plenty of room to grow as well.
But even then, like Taylor
Twell as a solo person has sold
$10 million worth of software.
To P H P developers.
Yeah.
That's pretty crazy.
That's insane.
And he just recently
took on employees.
So, um, you know, there's funded
startups in San Francisco right
now that have millions of dollars
in funding, uh, staff of 50
people, and they haven't sold
$10 million worth of software.
I think the market that you're
in determines everything and.
When you have, um, what Corey
Gwynn calls demonstrated
demand, so you can actually
see the demand, um, that's kind
of what you're looking for.
You're looking for people in
motion, a large group of people
in motion who are, where there's
economic activity being generated
from whatever they're doing.
Noah: So, yeah.
So you would basically say, start
out with the market, try to find a
market that you wanna work in, and
then start building your audience.
And around that, like, don't
worry as much about, uh, do
you feel comfortable, uh,
in that audience or Yeah.
Those kind of
Justin: things.
I mean, this is
where it gets tricky.
This is why business
is so hard because.
You have to, you apply all
of these filters to get to
right where you wanna go.
So it's like, it's not, it
can't, it's not enough to
just be in a good market.
You actually have to be
interested in that market.
You have to, you have good
founder market fit, you have
to, um, you know, you have to
then be able to identify some
sort of need in that market.
You have to, uh, then you have
to actually execute on some
things and, you know, make some,
make some sort of connection.
I don't think you have to naturally
necessarily build an audience, but
you get a lot of leverage from who
you know and who knows you, who you
know is just making connections.
We've, we're making
connections right now.
Now the three of
us know each other.
And, uh, even the fact that
we've been on a phone call makes
it a lot easier for me to ask
a favor of you in the future or
for you to ask a favor of me.
That's networking.
That's who you know, who knows
you, is the audience effect.
And, um, that, I mean,
that could be very helpful.
Uh, but there are people who,
who have built businesses
without doing that.
Uh, Ruben Gamma is a good example.
Of someone who's just built a
software business almost purely
on search engine results and
optimizing search engine results.
So I, I think it's one of
the levers you can use.
Uh, I think without any
sort of human connection,
it's very difficult.
So you have to, mm-hmm.
You do have to connect with
other human beings, and I get,
this is why it's helpful to be
interested in the market you're in.
Um.
And it's, sometimes it can
even, that can be enough.
Like I'm really interested
in the Laravel community.
I'm not really a Laravel
developer, but I've spoken at
their conference three times.
I really like the people and,
um, you know, uh, I would say
I'm part of the community even
though I, I'm not like a power
user of Laravel and mm-hmm.
Um, But, so there has
to be something that
draws you to that market.
There has to be something that
keeps you there, and you're
probably going to need some sort
of connection with some key people
in that market to make it work.
And it, you know, how you get there
is kind of the individual journey.
I'm, I'm almost 40 now,
and, you know, it's, it's
very difficult to say.
Um, you know, what are the 10 steps
that brought you to transistor?
Because it's like layer on,
layer on layer of my life
going back to when I was a kid.
And so all of those steps up till
now lead me to where I'm at now.
I think you can optimize
for some of those things.
Like where you point yourself
in life has a big determination
of where you'll end up, right?
Mm-hmm.
Uh, I think.
The, the connections
you make matter a lot.
I think what you put out
into the world matters a lot.
So, uh, you know, podcasting,
blogging, uh, public speaking, but
even just anything, uh, not, uh,
open source projects, anything you
put out into the world can help.
But in terms of like adding
all those up and going, okay,
what, what really matters.
A lot harder to to figure that out.
Yeah, I think
Ben: that's a pretty interesting
point because when we started
out with a podcast, I think we
were both like on the track of
we should build an audience.
And we just, it's kind of
like we are shifting, shifting
away from that a little bit.
Mm-hmm.
Um, and just recently came across
this tweet from Jane Portman and
I think Rob Walling, um, Jane
Portman from User List, um, who
were also talking about that, like
how they didn't really need an
audience and that basically just.
It, it just fits very well to
what you just said, I guess.
Mm-hmm.
Um, and there's one more thing
that I would like to like,
like get your opinion on, um,
because you're probably familiar
with, uh, Derek Rimer and what
happened with Level, right?
Mm-hmm.
Yeah.
It's kind of like, do you feel
like having an audience might
not al might not always be,
not necessary, but also maybe
like lead to false positives?
Justin: Mm-hmm.
Oh, definitely.
Yeah.
Uh, again, it can be
really helpful too.
Uh, there's to say that, um,
my audience didn't help in
launching transistor would
be disingenuous like that.
It definitely helped.
It still helps.
Um, but there is a risk
because what you're looking
for is you're looking for
some sort of momentum, right?
What and when you launch something,
You're trying to gauge what kind
of response is this getting?
So when Apple releases the
new iPhone, how many people
are lined up outside of
the Apple store right now?
Um, this Apple actually can fall
prey to this because they've
got all these mega fans, right?
Right that are gonna line
up day one no matter what.
So you could see these huge
lineups and you could go, oh
wow, like the new iPhone's a
big success, but unless the
rest of the world shows up, then
it's not going to be a success.
Right.
So yeah, that's a
pretty good analogy.
Yeah.
Lineups on day one.
I mean, they are helpful, but um,
they can, they can also, uh, you
know, like I've launched things.
I think still to this day, my
best launch ever was, uh, for
this, I was doing this online
series on product marketing and
like the first couple weeks,
tons of people showed up.
And when I started asking them,
what were you, what are you
hoping to achieve, you know, out
of this what brought you here?
They said, oh, I'm just a big fan.
I just get everything that you
put out and that's nice, but.
Uh, it became really
clear in the coming months
that no one else cared.
Hmm.
Uh, that's the disadvantage
of having an audience.
When people are really
kind of invested in your
journey, uh, they're gonna
show up no matter what.
They're gonna show up
just because they have a
personal connection to you.
But, uh, ultimately, if you're
gonna run a business, you need
people who are gonna show up.
And then more people were
gonna show up, and then more
people were gonna show up.
Right?
Uh, and, and this is actually
why I, I think the market
you choose matters so much.
And what I've gotten into
some public disagreements with
people who could be right.
I mean, they, these are my
friends and people I respect,
but the, the idea of going
after a small niche, I think.
And again, maybe people
are, I don't know.
The idea of going after a small
niche is just you're limiting
yourself to, let's say a
pool of 5,000, 10,000 people.
Well, that's like going to a little
tiny stream and trying to like
scoop up a little bit of water.
From a tiny stream as
opposed to going after a big,
massive market in motion.
That's like going to a rushing
river and just putting your
cup in the river and just
like scooping out a, you know?
Yeah.
And it, sure, you might be able
to fill up your cup just, you
know, at a small little stream.
But the rushing river has so
much water that it's, it's,
it's a lot easier for a solo
bootstrapper to just, you know,
put their cup in the river and
then scoop up a bunch of water.
And I think sometimes this
idea of niche is, uh, leads
people to the wrong places.
They're just looking for these
tiny streams that no one else
has ever discovered before.
Uh, where, you know, and
they say, well, we gotta
avoid the big rivers, because
everyone knows about those.
Yeah.
But it's a lot easier to get
your cup in a big river and,
and scoop out some water than
to find this tiny little thing
that nobody knows exists.
Yeah.
Ben: And the end, your cup
is bigger than the river.
Justin: Exactly.
Noah: Yeah.
I think, I wonder if where the
kind of disagreement that you
have with people about that
idea really just comes from like
the end goal with what people
want to do with their business.
Because basically where
I hear kinda what you're
saying, um, well, I guess
the opposite of what you say.
And that, you know, find a niche
market, the i'd, the advice
that I've typically seen that
from is places like Y Combinator
or, or startups that are really
trying to do like a go big
or go home kind of business.
Mm-hmm.
Um, like I think a good
example is, uh, Peter Thiel,
the, the co-founder PayPal.
His book Zero to One.
I don't know if you've
heard of that or mm-hmm.
Or, mm-hmm.
Or read it.
But I mean, that's almost
his whole thing is basically
go for the new markets.
Like that's where you
can make really, you can,
there's a lot of opportunity
to make a huge business.
And you know, that's kind of
like what, you know, PayPal,
Facebook, some of those
giant companies now did.
Mm-hmm.
Well, so yeah, if you're, if
people that are saying that
kind of advice are venture
capitalists or you know,
people that, that's their goal.
Then I, I could see that making
sense, but like, you know,
for bootstrappers, I think
that is then very dangerous.
Mm-hmm.
Um, and so maybe, I don't
know, I'm just wondering maybe
that's where the disconnect
is between those different
Justin: ideas.
Yeah, I think, I mean, part
of it is probably semantics.
Um, and part of it is this
is all really emotional stuff
because the way that you are
currently doing your thing, Kind
of informs your bias, the way
that you've achieved success
in the past informs your bias.
I mean, I said things at 20 years
old that I don't believe anymore.
I said things at 30 years old
that I don't believe anymore.
And so a lot of this is
just, you know, what, where
we're at and what's working
for us right now and mm-hmm.
I mean, I was on Twitter, this
guy Evan Golden was saying,
um, Uh, you can stretch
the definition pretty wide.
It's always easy to justify, you
know, people are spending money.
Um, oh, what did he say?
He said, people are spending
money on tacos everywhere,
so this could justify.
Mean opening attacker, stunt
featuring dirt flavored tacos.
There's lots of evidence.
People wanted tacos And Evan's
a friend of mine, but these
are the kind of arguments
I get into on Twitter.
Yeah, but I think that,
unfortunately, that's exactly
what I do wanna do, is I want
to say, is there any evidence
in this market of prior of
demonstrated demand, that's just
a great word, from Corey Gwynn.
Uh, and so PayPal, let's
take PayPal as an example.
What was, what was the market?
For what PayPal was doing
before PayPal existed?
Well, it was massive that the,
the, the Western Union, like
bank transfer, like, you know,
money transfer market, uh, people
trying to pay for things with
credit cards online, but having
to go through their credit card
processors and there's all sorts
of friction, but there's tons of
evidence that there's billions
of dollars being spent in that.
Market already.
And so it's not like
PayPal invented anything.
I mean, sure, they, they created
a new way of doing those things,
but they didn't create the market.
They were riding a wave
that already existed.
Uh, they just saw the wave
coming and they built a better
surfboard that, you know,
enabled them to ride further
than anyone else had at the time.
Uh, and, and this is what I'm
talking about, is really, and in
some ways, uh, What Evan is saying
is like, I am, I'm stretching
the definition to say, is there
any sort of prior or existing
demonstrated demand for this thing?
And I think you could see that in
almost every major product launch
like the iPhone, before the iPhone
was the Blackberry and the palm.
And you know, you can keep
going back and back and back.
Right.
There's, mm-hmm.
There's demonstrated
demand for these things.
Even if you look at, um, I
can remember as a kid looking
in catalogs, wanting to buy
a portable television right
from Radio Shack or whatever.
There was demand for portable.
Televisions that were
battery operated.
They never worked very well,
but there was demonstrated
demand for that thing.
Well, a big part of the iPhone
is just a portable television.
Right.
That's, at least that's how
my kids use it, that it's
like Netflix all day long.
Yeah, definitely.
Now, so I, I think the point
is to look for, Some sort of
demonstrated demand and, and to
think, is this a market in motion?
Is there evidence that
people are doing something
about this right now?
Um, so yeah.
Noah: Yeah.
So the, the market is
kind of being defined as.
Like a problem to be solved or
like a job to be done rather
than, I don't know, maybe how like
marketers sometimes think about
markets as almost, I feel like
they can kind of put it into a box
of like a specific solution or a
specific, uh, area in that way.
So yeah, really focusing
from what you're saying,
it sounds like, yeah.
Really focusing on the problem
that needs to be solved, is
that a big market of people,
you know, want that, you know?
Justin: Mm-hmm.
Yeah.
You, yes, exactly that.
That's, that's exactly
what I'm talking about.
The, the, there's lots, you,
you can see this with, uh,
if you go into Product Hunt
and you find, I run into this
all the time, products that
are no longer around, there's
all these like dead startups.
Oh yeah.
And in almost every case,
there just wasn't enough.
Demonstrated demand for that thing.
They were good ideas.
They, they kind of made sense
logically, but if you looked at
it and go, okay, but who's doing
something about this right now?
That's really what's most
interesting about Derek Reimer's
story is that once he started
talking to the people on his
waiting list, And asking,
okay, well what are you doing
about this problem right now?
Yeah.
And often their response
was, well, nothing.
We haven't done anything.
What?
You haven't searched on
Google for an answer.
No.
You haven't searched the
Slack extension store?
No.
Well that, that, that's a bad
sign if people aren't even willing
to do something free, which
is just search for a solution.
How are you gonna convince
them to jump over all of these
hurdles and actually take out
their credit card outta their
wallet and pay you for something?
Um, and this is another thing
I've maybe had a hard time to
articulate, is it it takes so
much momentum to get someone
to take out their credit card,
that you've gotta be sure
that what you're proposing.
Is something that they
really, really want.
And really the only way to, to
figure that out, the only way
to see that clearly is are they
doing something about it right
now, and is there enough of these
people on mass doing this, doing
something about it right now?
Ben: Yeah, I love
that piece of advice.
I actually thought that it's,
I, I think it was actually you
said that like, you should go to
Twitter and just search, search if
people are typing something like,
um, I don't know, like maybe even
using the, their grammar example.
Um, like search in Twitter
for switching away from Slack
or switch away from Slack.
Mm-hmm.
And see how many results
you actually find.
And there are a couple,
I did that for fun.
Um mm-hmm.
Mm-hmm.
Justin: But yeah, and I mean,
that's just step one, right?
Because it's.
It's pretty low friction to
tweet, um, your disappointment
with something, but at
least that's something.
And then, you know, you would
actually want to talk with folks
and ask them questions like, okay,
well, what caused you to switch?
How long did you think about
switching before it happened?
Uh, what, what did you have
to do internally in your team
to make that switch happen?
And that's where you're
gonna get a lot of answers.
It's one reasons I, I worked for
a, a project management software
startup, and what I didn't know
before I joined is how hard
it is to get people to switch
project management software.
And it's remarkably difficult
because, Everybody has an
opinion on the team, right?
Yeah.
The developers want one thing,
the marketing folks want one.
Another thing, the c t o
wants one thing, like it
goes around and around.
And so you have to convince
not just one person, but 10, 20
people to, to make this decision.
Uh, and then the, the
other kind of bad sign.
So despite how difficult it
is to get people to switch,
people do switch all the time.
And that's also a bad sign
because they don't just switch
once and then they're satisfied.
Yeah.
They switch, they try Trello,
and then they're like,
Nope, this didn't work.
And then they try Basecamp
and then they're like,
oh, that doesn't work.
And then they try Jira.
Like they all end up in Jira.
Right.
That's how it works.
Yeah.
Um, and so the, the, you know, when
you actually get into those real
discussions with people about what
does the actual process look like?
Um, Even, you know, a market
like project management,
it has its own, um, uh, it
its own minefield, right?
Like there's you, there's pros
and cons and, uh, I think for
Bootstrappers it's a lot harder.
It's why we've seen, you know,
Basecamp got in early and so
they've done okay, but really,
besides Basecamp, everybody else is
venture funded because you mm-hmm.
It just costs so much money.
Uh, and if you get on their
list, like people, they
will, JIRA will call you.
They will, like, they've
got salespeople that
wanna onboard you, right?
Because they know the only way
to push this through the whole
funnel is to have a lot of kind
of concerted effort doing it.
So a lot of these things, a lot of
these decisions depend on whether
or not you're bootstrapping,
whether or not you're
bootstrapping as a solo founder.
Because some of these ideas and
markets are just harder to reach as
a bootstrapper or a solo founder.
Noah: Right.
So with that like in mind and
you know, starting with the
market, I guess, and maybe
some ways what sounds like
what you'd say is basically
start with the market filter.
Mm-hmm.
Like that's the first filter
that you want to put on Yes.
Of how to, yes.
Uh, basically choose what
problem you're gonna solve,
how you're gonna do it.
Mm-hmm.
Um, how do you, like, it
seems like, you know, you
start talking to customers,
you start talking to users.
It takes a while before you can
really know what's the right
approach, what's the right solution
to actually build, what do you
do if that solution ends up being
something that isn't something
that a bootstrapper can do?
Mm-hmm.
Or it's.
Or it's, or, or maybe it's
a solution that doesn't
use your strengths.
Mm-hmm.
You know, as a, as a
founder, it doesn't use
your skills, your abilities.
Um, so how do you handle that when,
I guess, starting with a market?
Mm-hmm.
Because, yeah, I mean, I guess
it, in some ways it kind of
goes back to there's just all
these filters and in some ways
all these things have to align,
which is obviously very hard.
Justin: Yeah.
I mean, I think that's
just the, this is.
Another unpopular tweet of mine.
But my, it is just, and I had to, I
had to admit this before I had any
success, but what you kind of have
to admit in some way on one side
is we're not all gonna make it.
And a lot of people
don't like hearing that.
Um, but mm-hmm.
We're not all gonna make it there.
There's no way that every single
aspiring entrepreneur in the world,
Can apply all of these filters
and come out on the other side.
And by the way, even you come
out on the other side and you
know, like, I have a business
now that's doing pretty well.
It could disappear tomorrow.
Every day I wake up
going, well, maybe today's
the day it disappears.
Right?
Because markets change.
Mm-hmm.
And they can change really fast.
And so there's, there's no.
There's nothing really romantic
about starting a business.
It's just there's all sorts
of things that have to align
for it to work, and, um, a lot
of us aren't gonna make it.
So, so you have to hold, you
have to hold that on one side.
Well, at the same time,
on the other side, these
things are intention.
On the other side, you have
to be super optimistic that
you're going to make it.
And that you're just gonna
keep trying because, uh, the,
the other thing I've seen
anecdotally, I don't know if this
is scientific, but the people who
keep trying, who keep working at
it, who keep pushing that ball
forward, many of them do make it.
And so there's a, there's a little
bit of how long can you last?
How long can you try?
Mm-hmm.
Um, it's why a lot of successful
entrepreneurs actually tend
to be statistically older.
Because by that point in
your life, you've had a
bunch of industry experience.
So you know what an industry is.
You know, you've got connections
in that industry, you've
seen the pain points, you've
seen how they spend money.
You, you know, there's all of this
accrued experience that ends up
being helpful and um, you know,
it time is kind of what allows
you to keep pushing, right.
I.
So it's not saying you
shouldn't try in your twenties,
but because you could, it
could all align, right?
My friend Nathan Barry is
not even 30 yet and has
already achieved more as a
founder than a lot of folks.
Um, but I think you have to have
this idea of, well, it might not
happen, but I'm gonna try and
this might be a 10 year project or
this might be a 20 year project.
And, uh, you almost have
to be okay with that.
Like, This just might take time
for everything to align and
the whole time I'm going to
have to be working as if this
will eventually work out and
not just doing the same thing.
Putting yourself in new
circles, getting outside
of your comfort zone.
I've described this before as,
uh, is it, uh, command and conquer
that uses fog of war where you're
just on a map and everything's
dark and you're exploring it?
Yeah.
So if you think about that as a
metaphor, like when you start out,
you're just in that map and all
you can see is around you, right?
And as you explore more
of the map, more and more
parts become illuminated.
And every once in a while you'll
end up in a spot of the map
where things just happen, right?
Like you get a bunch of
bounty or you run into a
bunch of enemies or whatever.
And it's kind of like that.
Like you're, you're walking around.
For me, for example, I was walking
around and I just happened to run
into Adam Wain, who I had no idea
who he was or anything about him,
but he ended up being quite an
influential person in the Laravel
community, and that was just me
wandering around the map and hit
him wandering around the map too.
And then us.
Uh, meeting each other and once,
once I could see, like I've learned
tons about, a lot of my thoughts
about like choosing a market first
have been because of the influence
of the Laravel community and
looking at Taylor and Adam Wain,
and Steve Stroger and Jeffrey
Way build these crazy businesses
because in my little world
before I met them, you know, I.
This is the way things were done.
People like us do things like this.
And then I got over into that
area of the map and it was like
this whole new world opened
up that I'd never seen before.
And without that world opening
up, I don't think I would've,
um, well, I, I don't think a
lot of things would've happened.
And so there's clearly you
have to kind of be always
doing things, trying things,
getting outta your comfort zone.
Meeting new people.
And I think the advice I
would give my kids is just to
explore as much of the map as
you can, as early as you can.
Yeah.
'cause the, the more
exploration you do.
I, I think I stayed
too local too long.
You know, I grew up in this small
little farming town in Alberta and
then the big city was Edmonton and
I just spent too much time there.
And then, you know, like the
first time I flew into New
York, I was like, holy shit.
Like there's a lot of people here.
There's a lot of money here.
Yeah.
There's a lot of businesses
here that I've never even
imagined before and it kind of
expanded my whole worldview.
And unless you're doing that work
to kind of walk around the map
and discover new, new areas, um,
yeah, I think I, I think it'll be
harder to, you know, to, to find
those markets, to find those ideas.
Yeah.
Noah: So, uh, I want to go back
a little bit to something you
said, you know, kind of talking
about how, um, basically this,
this might not work for all of us.
Mm-hmm.
And it's very hard and.
Um, yeah, we all might not make
it through, and that's just
kind of the, the truth of it.
Yeah.
So like how do you, and I'm just
curious about your situation,
like how do you go to your wife
with that and get her on board
for this whole journey of what
we're trying to do, because.
So that's, I'm just curious
'cause that's definitely
something I know me and my
wife struggle with, um, a lot.
Mm-hmm.
Just with, with my last
thing and like, it is hard.
So it's like it's, you know,
you're, it's not just you going
on this journey, you're bringing
your whole family with you.
Yeah.
Justin: I mean, again, you probably
don't wanna look at the statistics.
The, the statistics are pretty bad.
Ben: Just don't look.
So this podcast has to be
titled Unpopular Opinions.
Justin: Unpopular
Opinions and Jokes.
I mean, it's just like, if
you want the reality, the
reality's not good statistically.
Um, I mean, clearly I think,
I think all entrepreneurs have
this feeling that maybe they can
do it better than the next guy.
And because statistically,
you know, millions of people
start businesses, but.
Uh, those people are in all sorts
of different places, have all
sorts of different leverage, have
all sorts of different privilege.
You know, there's, there's all
these factors that go into, you
know, why a person becomes a
successor, not, and I think every
entrepreneur feels like they've
got some secret sauce that'll make
them better than the next guy.
Oh, yeah.
But I mean, In my early twenties,
I started a couple retail shops
that ended up losing a lot
of money, and that was hard
to recover from as a family.
And so mm-hmm.
That, that is just part of it,
like if you're gonna be on that.
So that was almost 20 years ago.
And, uh, So now I'm at a place
where, you know, maybe I've
learned enough lessons and
I've made enough connections
that things are happening,
but that's a long journey.
That's 10, 20 years
of, of, uh, work.
And so, yeah, I mean, I think
that's something you gotta consider
with kind of, with everything.
Um, I, I don't think you should
kill yourself in the process.
I think.
I think I worked probably
too hard a lot of those
years when I didn't need to.
It was just wasted cycles
trying to make something happen.
You know, you're, you're, it's
far better for you to book a
ticket to a conference that
you've never been to than to
work 60, 70, 80 hours a week.
Um mm-hmm.
Because at least for me, the,
the biggest jumps forward
have been because I met
somebody outside of my circle.
I met John Buddha, the, my
co-founder in 2014 at this kind
of experimental technology art
design festival called xo xo.
And you know, I wasn't gonna
go initially, I had to kind of
push myself to get outta the
house and, and actually go.
So yeah, I, I don't think
there's any easy answers there.
I think you can stair
step your way up.
You can.
Um, do something small on the side
and then see if that evolves into
something bigger and then something
bigger and then something bigger.
Nathan Barry just wrote a piece
on this that I don't fully
like or agree with, but, um,
maybe I don't like it just
because it's the hard truth.
Uh, he talks about a series
of ladders and you know,
the first ladder is just
like trading time for money.
And then you kind of work
up that ladder, right?
You can work yourself up from
making minimum wage up to
making more money per hour,
but then you go to the next
ladder, which has higher earning
potential, but it's harder.
It's just like, okay, now you've
got to, you're trading time
for money, but it's, it's more
on your terms like consulting.
And so then you work your way
up that that level, uh, and
then there's another ladder.
And, you know, these keep
going and the difficulty with
each ladder goes up and, but
your, your potential, in his
case, he, he's just talking
about income earning potential.
Your income earning mm-hmm.
Potential goes up as well.
Um, and it is a little bit
of a stair step, right?
Like your moving your way up here
and then you're like, oh, well
there's opportunity over here.
So then you might take a few
steps back to start here and
then build yourself up here.
And then you look at the
next slide, you go, there's
more opportunity over there.
So then you go back down
and then work your way up.
Um, it, yeah, that's all possible.
Definitely helps if you have, uh,
in terms of like, uh, having a,
a decent life, it helps if you
have a lot more cash saved up.
Mm-hmm.
The more cash you have saved
up, the less stress you have.
Um, but that's not always
possible either, right?
So the, the, uh, the only way I can
think of to alleviate the stress
is to have very low cost of living
and, or a lot of money saved up.
Yeah.
Money that you can risk that you
wouldn't feel bad about losing.
So, and you can even hear
this in John and I's podcast.
You know, um, he was working for
Cards Against Humanity when we
started this, and he also had
more money saved up than I I did.
And so my stress level
when we weren't quite yet
full-time yet was a lot higher.
I'm just like, oh God.
Like do we gotta take investment?
Do we gotta try to add three
or four more things on top
of this to make this work?
You can see how like desperation,
um, Affects your actions.
And a lot of businesses you'll
see do this, like one thing's
not working quite enough.
So then they add another
thing to hopefully bring up
in more income, and that's
not quite bringing enough.
So they add another thing and
they just keep adding more
and more stuff and more and
more stress to their lives.
Uh, but yeah, for, for
John, yeah, it's easy.
He's got no dependence and uh,
his cost of living's low and he
had a bunch of money saved up.
It's like for him.
Yeah.
This isn't, that's easier.
This isn't make it or break it.
It's like, no, I can just, if
this doesn't work, yeah, I'm fine.
So that if you wanna make it
easier, I think lower your
expenses and save a bunch of
money or, Get someone to give
you a bunch of money or rob a
bank, a rob a bank, or whatever.
Noah: That goes
Justin: easy route.
I mean, this is why privilege
plays such a big part in business.
Like some people do.
They, they get a, they
have a big trust fund and
they get a bunch of money.
I.
It does help.
Yeah.
I
Ben: agree.
Noah: Yeah.
Yeah, that makes sense.
So maybe as a last question,
we could end with maybe you've
heard, uh, the, how I built
this podcast, they always end
with an interesting question.
Mm-hmm.
Which is, so for you, I'm just
interested in hearing as well,
like, With transistor, like
where you guys gotten so far,
how much do you think of that
was luck and how much of it
was, you know, you and John's
skill and talents and hard work?
Justin: It's definitely the
accumulation of a lifetime
of experience and I think, I
think your attitude matters
a lot in that, right?
Like are you gonna
keep going out and.
Trying things.
Are you gonna keep going out
and trying to push the envelope?
and put things out in public?
Are you going to go
out and meet people?
Like if, if, if you were gonna
split test my life and he put
one Justin in his room and he
never leaves and all he does is
play Sonic the Hedgehog forever.
And then you have another
version where he's like, always.
Going out and trying to figure
things out and trying to build
things and trying to write and
trying to meet this person.
And for sure in that AB test,
you know, Justin b uh, wins.
There's, I don't think
it's, that's a, it's not
too difficult to see that.
So yeah, there's a lot of luck
in where I was born and, um, But
you're the, the, the, the influence
of luck starts to go down a lot.
Like the, the, the, the
influence of blind luck.
Like just like where you were
born, like what, what year
and country and location and
parents you were born to.
After that part, you make your
most of your luck just by whatever
attitude you have every day.
Mm-hmm.
There's still some privilege
that comes with where you were
born, but most of that kind of
built in luck is already happened
by the time you were born.
Noah: Yeah.
Cool.
Well, thanks Justin for coming on.
That was a good conversation.
Very helpful for both of
us and hopefully, I'm sure
for our listeners as well.
Hopefully I didn't bum
Justin: you out too much.
No,
Noah: I mean, sometimes you
need a little of that, get
you back, back to the truth.
Um, so yeah, thanks Justin.
And we will, uh, see you
guys in another episode
Ben: and we'll put
everything in the show notes.
All right.
Bye.
See you.