This is Transistor.fm.
Hey, product people.
Justin Jackson here, and I've
got a brand new interview for
you with James Clear, who
is the author of Atomic Habits,
a book that has really changed
my life since I've read
it.
And I don't want to give too
much of an intro.
I just want to get right into
the actual interview.
If you like this, please reach
out to James on Twitter @JamesC
lear.
And if you have comments about
the episode, reach out to me on
Twitter.
I'm the letter M, the letter I,
Justin, M, I, Justin.
Here is me and James talking
about habits and how you can
make your life better one
day at a time.
The book, your book's been out
for a while.
It's right here, Atomic Habits.
If you see it in an airport or
something near you, how long
has it been out now?
Today is 100 days exactly.
No way.
Yeah, so just over three months
.
I'm curious, because now it's
been out for a while.
Is there one idea that you see
that people keep sharing, like
one idea that resonated
from the book in particular
that gets shared more than
anything else on Twitter or
whatever?
So I was curious about that
myself when I was writing the
book and thinking about it,
because I kind of felt like,
all right, hopefully all these
ideas are useful.
What's the one thing that
people are going to latch on to
?
Because sometimes you'll hear
that from authors that there
was one chapter or something
that
was the chapter that really
stuck with people.
I'm grateful for the fact that
there are a variety of things,
but there are a few things.
So the first one is identity-
based habits, which is chapter
two.
And that concept really seems
to have resonated with people,
the idea of trying to reinforce
your desired identity and
starting with who you want to
become rather than what you
want
to achieve.
And I'm glad that it did,
because that was the chapter I
debated over the most of where
to put it in the book.
At different points, it was the
first chapter.
It was the last chapter.
It ended up being the second
one.
I also had this thought in my
head that it should be about
midway through the book.
So it really jumped all over
the place, but I ended up
thinking, I feel like this is
one
of the best ideas, so I want to
have it early so that people,
even if they don't finish
the book, they still come
across this idea.
And I'm glad that that ended up
working out well.
The other one that people bring
up a lot is the two-minute rule
and the idea of scaling
your habits down to the point
where they take two minutes or
less.
I think that that's a very
actionable one.
It's like, OK, I know exactly
what to do.
I wanted to do a workout, but
now I'll just focus on doing
five push-ups.
Or I wanted to read 30 books
this year, and now I'll focus
on reading one page a day or
something like that.
Got you.
So I think the actionableness
of that one also tends to stick
.
And so going back to the
identity one, is this the idea
that every action you take or
every habit you develop is a
vote for the person you want to
become?
Right.
So that's kind of like my core
philosophy behind it, this idea
that the way that we develop
beliefs about ourselves, that
we reinforce our self-image,
that we develop our identity
to a certain degree, is largely
reinforced by the experiences
and behaviors that we perform
over time.
So some aspects of your
identity are relatively fixed,
like, for example, if you're
tall or
short.
Even that idea that I am tall
or I am short, that's
reinforced.
You learn that through
experiences in life.
Now there are many aspects of
your identity that are less
fixed than that, but are still
reinforced by your experiences.
So if you write one sentence
today, you probably don't think
about yourself as I am a writer
.
But if you do that every day
for six months or nine months
or a year, at some point you
turn around and you think, "Huh
, maybe I am the kind of person
who is a writer."
Or if you study biology every
Tuesday night for 20 minutes,
you at some point think, "I
guess I'm studious.
I keep doing this every week.
Maybe this is the kind of
person I am."
And so I like that idea that
our habits are like votes for
the type of person we believe
that we are, that they build up
evidence of looking at
ourselves in a certain way.
And I like to phrase it that
way not only because I believe
that it's true, but also
beliefs and behavior are kind
of a two-way street.
So you'll hear people say
things like, "Just be positive
or just believe in yourself or
fake it till you make it," or
things like that.
And there's nothing necessarily
wrong with fake it till you
make it.
It's fine to be positive and
believe things about yourself,
but it's a very short-term
strategy because fake it till
you make it is asking you to
believe something about
yourself
without having evidence for it.
It's like that kind of
visualization stuff or mantra
stuff where you look at
yourself
in the mirror and you tell
yourself, "I am a writer.
I am a writer," even though you
haven't written yet.
And so what I'm saying is
similar, but I think
importantly different in the
sense that you
let the behavior lead the way
rather than the belief.
And I think that's the best
lever we have for changing the
way that we look at ourselves,
which is to say, show up and
write a sentence every day, and
soon you're going to have
something
to root that new identity of, "
I am a writer in."
And it's a much more, I think,
robust and long-term way of
changing how you look at
yourself.
Yeah, I think for me the...
Because you first communicated
that idea to me in an airport
in Denver.
Yeah, I remember that.
And at the time in my life, I
was not doing so good.
I was depressed.
I was, I think, cynical.
Especially, I think cynical
about people like you that seem
to have it all together, that
seem to be really like doing
all the good habits.
And when you're not doing so
good, looking at someone that
seems to have it all together
just can make you more grumpy
or more cynical or more
whatever.
But I remember you sitting down
and kind of hashing this out
with me.
And that idea of, "Justin, no
matter where you're at right
now and no matter what you've
done, you could start today
with one action."
So if you go running today,
that might not make a big
difference.
And then if you do it tomorrow
and then the next day and then
the next day and then the
next day, at the end of the
week, you might say, "Well,
wait a second.
I think I'm a runner."
And maybe after a couple of
weeks, you might say, "Well, I
'm going to get myself some
runner
clothes and go and get some
runner clothes.
And then I'm going to get
myself a good pair of...
Shoot, I'm going to install
that Strava app."
And all of a sudden you could
see yourself.
That was a really hopeful
message for me when I was
really struggling to figure out
.
It was way easier for me to be
cynical and just kind of look
back at all these people
implementing good, healthy
processes and say, "Well, that
's not for me.
That's just for people that
whatever."
But seeing, hearing that gave
me hope to think, "I could do
that.
And it's surprising how little
time it takes to accomplish
that.
Is that something...
Have other people been kind of
referencing that too?
Is that part of the...
And maybe that's what's so good
about having it as chapter two
because it gives me some
hope, right?
Right, yeah.
Well, what's interesting is
that that process of changing
in that way, it's happening
anyway.
If you think back to the
beginning, for example, if I
think of the early days of my
entrepreneurial
career, well, I didn't have any
entrepreneurs in my family.
I didn't have any close friends
who were entrepreneurs.
There was no reason for me to
think that's who I am or to
feel like I was externally
validated with that was part of
my identity.
I had no evidence of it.
And so early on, all I had was
hope, right?
The hope that, "Oh, maybe I'll
be able to build something.
Maybe I'll be able to make this
work."
But then you start to show up,
and for me, it was probably
about two years in.
It's probably about where I
kind of like the scale tipped,
and I started to think, "I am
an entrepreneur.
That's part of who I am."
But it really took proving it
to myself that I can pay my
bills through this, that I can
like actually have a lifestyle
and a career in this way.
I had to prove it for about two
years before I really started
to latch onto it and say,
"This is who I am."
And so my point is, that's
always happening.
You're continually updating
your beliefs about yourself
based on the experiences that
you're
going through.
And all I'm talking about is
simply designing that process
in a little more careful or
thoughtful
way rather than just kind of
letting it happen to you and be
like, "Well, I guess I'll
figure
out who I am based on what life
throws at me versus how about I
figure out who I am based
on the votes that I cast each
day and what habits I decide to
follow?"
Yeah, yeah.
Again, that is a very hopeful
message for someone who's just
kind of sitting back and
waiting for it to happen.
What sustains you when you're
in the process but not there
yet?
Like you mentioned entrepreneur
and you're like, "Man, it took
a long time."
What sustains you?
Good question because I think a
lot of habits, entrepreneurship
is certainly this way, exercise
is this way where the rewards
of a habit are often very
delayed.
What's the reward for working
out for three weeks?
Not really a whole lot,
honestly.
Your body hasn't really changed
.
The scale is probably about the
same.
You're probably just sore.
There probably isn't a whole
lot to show for it.
It's really not unless you
stick with that habit for three
months or six months or a
year that you actually start to
see the changes you were hoping
to get when you set out.
There's this valley of death in
the beginning where in a way it
gets harder before it gets
easier.
It feels uncomfortable.
You feel sore and pain.
You feel uncertain when you
walk in the gym.
You feel like people are
judging you.
Same way with starting a
business.
In a weird way, it's harder
before it gets easier.
You start out, but you're not
making any money.
You feel stupid a lot of the
time because you don't know how
to make a sales call or
what customers are looking for
or whether you're even offering
the right product.
I remember when I first started
, like I said, I didn't know
anybody.
Didn't have any entrepreneurs
in my family.
I was like, "Well, I need to
get to know some people."
I sent a bunch of emails to
reach out and just ask if
people would chat on Skype for
like 30 minutes or whatever.
I remember sending those first
few and thinking, "Do people
even do this?
Do people chat on Skype with
people that they haven't met
before?
Is this a weird thing to ask?"
There's just a lot of that
uncertainty early on.
Your point is, I think, a valid
one, which is, "Well, what do
you do to get through that?
How do you get through that
valley of death while you're
waiting for the long-term
rewards
to accumulate?"
I think that this is where
psychologists call it
reinforcement or an external
reinforcer,
that you want some kind of
reinforcement that is enjoyable
in the moment so that you have
a reason to keep showing up.
There are from a habit
standpoint, there are two ways
to do this.
First thing is just a strategic
choice about what type of habit
you choose to follow.
If we go back to the exercise
example, well, not everybody
has to work out like a body
builder.
You could do Pilates or yoga or
go for a run or rock climbing
or all kinds of stuff.
Pick the form of a habit that
brings you the most joy, that
is most enjoyable to you.
It's going to be a slog for,
you're going to have to swim
for months to see a change
in your body.
You're going to have to cycle
for months.
You're going to have to lift
weights for months.
It doesn't really matter which
one you choose.
It's going to take a while.
You might as well choose the
one that's most exciting or
enjoyable to you.
Same way with like, imagine a
reading habit.
You don't have to read.
You might feel like, "Oh, I
have a business, so I need to
read business books."
But really ultimately, the most
important thing is do you get
in the habit of reading?
Do you fall in love with
reading?
If you need to start with sci-
fi books or fantasy or something
like that, well, start
with that.
Do the one that is intrins
ically valuable to you at first.
Once the habit is built, then
you can transition to some of
the other stuff.
That's one method for getting
through that valley of death.
Yeah.
I think this brings up maybe a
harder question, which is, so
based on your book, it's
January
and I'm thinking, "Okay, I
haven't been in the gym for
seven years.
I used to love working out.
I'm going to go.
I got my streaks app on my
phone.
Start going."
I've probably been, I don't
know, I've probably been at
least 18 days or maybe even 20
days
this month.
It's great.
I was surprised by how fast I
felt.
The first day, I felt like I
didn't belong.
I felt awkward.
I don't know anybody here I'm
walking in.
Some of the machinery, I
recognize.
Some I don't.
I have to get back into a
routine.
I have to find which exercise I
'm going to do.
There's all these insecurities
and questions.
But after a week, I felt like I
belonged.
But I wonder if that's because
it was easier for me.
I had this, I'm relatively, I
was already relatively in shape
.
There's a big difference
between going in where you feel
like, "Oh, maybe I'm a few
pounds overweight."
Going in and being 200 pounds
overweight.
There's a big difference
between going in even as a
white male compared to, there's
a big difference going in and
feeling like, "Well, I've done
these exercises before so
I'm not completely out of my
element."
And I'm wondering how, I mean,
are habits like that achievable
because of privilege
and context and other things.
How much does that play into it
?
And if someone is walking in
and they're 200 pounds
overweight, do they still have
the
same chance of progress and
success?
It just feels like such a big
mountain for them to go over.
For sure.
Yeah.
So, this is one reason why I
think starting with small
habits is so incredibly
important
because a lot of the time when
we think about the outcome that
you want, so just to continue
your weight loss or exercise
example, everybody gets wrapped
up and like, "Oh, I want to
lose
100 pounds or I want to lose 20
pounds or whatever the number
is."
But you forget about there,
like all these little log
istical and emotional details
that
come along with starting a new
habit.
So I'll often tell the story
about, I have this reader who,
he ended up losing over 100
pounds.
And one of the first things he
did was he went to the gym, but
he wasn't allowed to
stay for longer than five
minutes.
So he drove to the gym, got out
of the car, did half an
exercise, got back in the car,
drove home.
And it sounds ridiculous to
people.
It sounds silly because it's
like, "Well, clearly exercising
for five minutes is not
going to get you in shape."
I guess not.
But what you realize is he was
mastering the art of showing up
.
He was becoming the type of
person that drove to the gym
every day.
And when you're in that state,
for him at that point, that was
the biggest shift was,
"Can I just become the type of
person who gets in here, who
overcomes the uncertainty
or feeling uncomfortable or
feeling judged?"
And all those things are very
real hurdles to building a
habit.
There are all these little
questions that need to be
answered for something like
that.
Like, "Okay, I want to go to
the gym.
Well, what time am I going to
go?
Am I going to go before work or
after work?
What gym will I go to?
What route am I going to take
to get there?
Do I need to bring a water
bottle or is there like a water
fountain at the gym?"
And all those little questions
like that, like whether or not
there's a water fountain
at the gym, it sounds small.
But if you already feel
uncomfortable and feel like you
don't belong and then you
always
forget to bring your water
bottle and you're like, "Oh,
there's nothing ever, and there
's
never anything to drink there."
That's enough friction to get
you to quit in the beginning.
So starting with something
simple, like, "All I'm going to
do is I'm going to show up and
I'm going to do one exercise
for five minutes and then I'm
going to go."
That I think is a good way to
start.
And it reminds me of what
Steven Pressfield wrote.
I think it was in the War of
Art where he said something to
the effect of like, "If
you sit down each day at the
computer and you do your
writing, at some point, at
first
it feels uncomfortable, but at
some point that becomes your
territory."
And I really like that phrasing
of it because for an animal,
for a wolf or something, a
piece of land does not become
their territory unless they
spend time in it, right?
Unless they are there each day.
It has to become comfortable
first.
And so for many people building
habits, whether that's getting
into the gym or going to the
yoga studio or sitting your
butt in the chair and writing,
you need to make that space
your
territory.
And the very first step is not
getting a result.
It's spending time there.
It's making that little bit of
land a zone where you feel like
, "This is where I belong
each day."
And that's a big emotional
hurdle to cross before you even
worry about any of the physical
or actual technical things to
do.
Yeah.
And I mean, the other thing
that helped is I went with my
wife and it's funny because
I felt like I'm like Mr. Conf
ident, but she was like, at one
point, she's like, "Justin,
you are so nervous right now."
She could tell how nervous I
was.
But I thought I was keeping it
all together.
And it just reminded me of, I'd
been to gyms from the time I
was in grade nine all the
way through college.
It wasn't like it was
unfamiliar, but I was nervous
because it was unfamiliar.
There had been a seven-year gap
and now I was exploring this
again, worried about what
these people are thinking about
me.
"Wow, that guy looks like he's
way more fit than me."
All these thoughts go through
your head.
And so, yeah, I think kind of
figuring out how you can make a
step and sometimes maybe
it's like going with somebody
so you at least have some
emotional, because it's
emotional.
It's nice to have someone to
kind of share the emotional
burden, right?
For sure.
Well, if you come, the thing
that ultimately what you're
looking to do is, like we just
said, feel like it's part of
your territory.
And because there are other
people in that space, what that
also means is you're looking
to feel like you're part of the
tribe who goes there, right?
You belong with the other
people who are in that room.
And so it helps to, what is a
tribe?
Well, it's a group of people
that you get along with, that
you bond with, that you belong
to over something else, over
some shared interest.
And in other words, it's a
group in a lot of ways of
friends, friends who share some
kind of interest.
So these are your gym friends.
Well, if you go with your wife,
then you automatically have at
least one person in the tribe
that
you are friends with, that you
do belong with.
And so I think that helps you
get over that hurdle a little
bit.
You're no longer facing that
challenge alone.
Before it was like, I am trying
to get fit.
Now it is we are trying to get
fit.
And that helps a lot with the
kind of the mental feeling of
like, do I belong or not?
Yeah.
So I don't mean to stay on this
too long, but it's so fresh
that the other thing I found
myself doing, because I'm
interested in the emotional
friction behind habits.
And so the other thing I was
doing is I was going in there
and I'm uncomfortable.
So I'm trying to act really
tough, but I'm not tough at all
.
But when people look at me, I'm
kind of like scowling when like
I'm not being friendly.
I'm not being myself.
And I was thinking about that
and thinking like when you're
kind of inward focused and
you're in a new environment and
you're trying to develop a new
habit, but you're inward
focused,
it really is, it doesn't really
help.
And so I had to kind of turn
that around and go, okay, I got
to start being friendly.
I got to start saying hi to
these people, because if I wave
at this person and it feels
good, like they respond with a
smile.
And that happens again next
time.
And again, next time, that's a
little bit of a reward for me.
That's going to keep me going
to the gym.
But if I keep going here with
this like tough scowl on my
face, and it's hard because you
feel like you don't belong.
You feel nervous.
And you kind of default to
these weird behaviors.
And it took a little bit of
time, but I realized, okay, now
I got to get in the habit of
smiling
and saying hello when I'm in
the gym, not just being like in
my own zone and pretending
I'm somebody I'm not, right?
Well, that's one thing that
kind of helps you start to
belong or become part of the
rest of the tribe.
Just a friendly behavior helps
you start to develop
friendships with some of those
other
people that are there.
Yeah.
A study that I wanted to cite
in Atomic Habits, but I couldn
't find it to track it down.
But I read about it years ago,
where the YMCA ran a survey.
And when they surveyed people
who were joining the gym, the
thing that got them to join
were
the different classes offered,
the equipment that was in the
gym, basically facilities
and features were the things
that got people in for the
first time.
But then when they surveyed
members who had been there for
over a year, the thing that
got people to stick, nobody
mentioned features or
facilities.
Everybody mentioned friendships
.
And so the people who actually
stayed at the gym or kept their
membership were the ones
who ended up developing
friendships with other people
there.
And I think you're right.
Ultimately, the thing that gets
you to come back is like, do I
enjoy coming here?
Does it mean I get to see some
of my friends?
Does it mean I get to hang out
with people I like?
Or, you know, it's really the
sense of belonging that gets
habits to stick.
And the action itself is just
kind of like something that's
happening along the way.
Yes.
But there's a step before that
that we kind of skipped over,
which is like, how do you
even choose a habit in the
first place?
Like how does that happen?
In the sense of, I might not
know what's good for me.
So how does that come into this
?
Yeah.
Well, there are a lot of ways
to answer that question.
So I'll just share a couple of
thoughts that come to mind.
So the first thought that comes
to mind is this question from,
I first heard from Seth
Godin, which I think is just a
great question, which is, what
is it for?
And so this is a question that
we need to ask ourselves when
we're trying to build a
new habit, which is, what is
this habit for?
What am I actually trying to
achieve here?
Because the correct habit to
choose is very different based
on what your goals are, what
you're hoping to get as an
outcome, what kind of lifestyle
you want.
And so for example, the habit
of making 20 sales calls a day.
Well, if what it's for is to
increase revenue and to build a
successful business, that's
a wonderful thing.
If you hate making sales calls
and you want to spend less time
working and more time with
your family, that could be a
terrible habit to build.
It just depends on what it's
for.
So that's one question to ask,
but you are correct that we
often don't know what we need
in the moment.
And I think part of that is
just a challenge of life and a
challenge of self-awareness
and knowing what you need, but
life is a very complex system.
And so figuring out the right
thing for that is sometimes
just impossible or too many
moving
parts.
So I tend to default to two
possible answers.
The first answer is, we all
need things that are so boring
that we don't think about them,
but are incredibly important
for showing up each day.
So did you sleep eight hours?
Are you drinking enough water?
Are you spending a little bit
of time walking outside or
getting a little bit of
sunlight?
Do you exercise consistently?
Whatever form is interesting to
you?
Are you spending some time
reading and soaking up new
ideas?
I'm not saying you have to do
all that stuff every day, but
my point is those are things
that most people would be like,
"Yeah, of course, you should
sleep and read more books
and exercise.
Everybody knows that's good."
But your time is almost never
going to be wasted by making
sure you do one of those things
.
It's a fundamental that's worth
spending time on that's worth
coming back to, that's worth
reminding yourself of, even if
you aren't sure the ideal
perfect place to focus in your
life.
So that's the first answer.
Come back to the fundamentals.
The second answer is more broad
.
I can't be specific with it
because it depends on each
person, but the broad
application
is what I would call broad
funnel tight filter.
So whenever you're trying to
figure out where to focus, you
need a really broad range of
research, try to get as many
options as possible, then apply
a really tight strict filter to
it and just focus on the one or
two best options that you found
.
So for example, I just finished
Atomic Habits a few months ago,
so now I'm thinking, "Should
I write a second book?
If I should, what should that
be about?"
And I don't know right now, so
I'm in the broad funnel stage.
So I want to lay out as many
options as possible.
I want to brainstorm a thousand
titles.
I want to look at all the top
books on Amazon.
I want to browse my best
performing tweets and see if
there's a possible thread for a
book idea in there.
I want to look everywhere I can
and just list all of that stuff
in the same spreadsheet.
And maybe I got 1200 ideas on
there, really broad funnel.
But then I need to apply a very
tight filter.
Is this something I'm
interested in enough to spend
two or three or four years
working
on?
Is it a topic of broad appeal
to a general audience?
Are there going to be a lot of
people that like this?
Is this something that I can
actually turn into something
actionable?
Can people use this in their
daily life?
Is this a topic that has a lot
of stories that I could tell?
Can I actually make this
entertaining or latch on to
other interesting stories to
make the
book readable?
Yes.
And those are just some of the
filters.
But my point is that you want
some period of very broad
exploration, and then once you
have a lot of options, you want
to really tighten it down based
on that question, what
is this for?
So in my case, the question I'm
using is, well, it's for
writing a good book, one that's
highly actionable, one that
sells a lot of copies, one that
people find useful, and so
on.
And so I think if you combine
that broad funnel type filter
strategy and that question of
what is it for, that can maybe
give you some more specific
answers.
But even if you don't come up
with something good there, you
can always focus on the
fundamentals.
And the other thing, when you
mentioned Seth Godin, he has
this other line, which is
people
like us do things like this.
I love that line.
I wish I had thought it up, but
yeah, it's so good.
It's such a great mantra.
And what's interesting about it
is, like for me, one thing that
made me start thinking
about healthy habits was
hanging out with people who had
healthy habits.
And in some ways, it was really
lucky and fortunate, like you
guys invited me to that
retreat you did.
And in some ways, I'm thankful
you guys invited a loser like
me, because I was hanging out
in that group.
I came and at first I was
cynical and grumpy.
And eventually, just looking
around that group, I realized,
man, these people like this do
things like this.
And my cynicism, which before
it would have been like, wow,
people like that do stuff like
that.
It went down.
And then all of a sudden I was
like, okay, well, if people
like this do things like this,
that's what I need to do.
And I think for folks that are
thinking like, okay, well, how
do I know what good habits
are?
There are so many things that I
would have never been, what do
you call it?
There's the stages of habits or
whatever.
But I would have never even had
the cue if I had not first
observed it and then noticed
like, oh wait, they're doing
that.
They're doing that.
I'm the odd man out.
And that's what motivated me to
want to pursue some of that
stuff.
But if I hadn't been in that
group and felt like, wait a
second, like, if I want to
belong
here, I've got to up my game,
right?
It would have never happened.
And so people like us do things
like this has been really
helpful for me.
Yeah, I love that phrase.
And one of the reasons I said
that, oh, I wish I had thought
that up, is because I think
it applies so deeply to a lot
of the ideas in Atomic Habits.
It applies to how socially
reinforced our habits are.
I think this is, you know, I
wrote about this in the book.
I mean, I have a whole chapter
on it.
Chapter nine is all about that.
But I think I still undersold
the importance of how socially
reinforced our habits are.
And then it also references the
importance of a shared identity
.
I think that ultimately a
shared identity is really one
of the most powerful forces for
getting habits to stick.
You know, like if you look at,
if you look at it in a big way,
you can look at like religions,
you know, people, religions are
really interesting places to
look for habits.
People get in the habit of
going to church every Sunday
for 50 years, largely because
it's reinforced.
The other people in their
neighborhoods go, the people on
their block go, they see their
friends there.
They, it's a very socially
reinforced habit.
Same thing is true in smaller
ways.
Like let's say you move into a
new house and you walk outside
on Tuesday night and you
see all your neighbors have
their recycling bins out.
And you're like, huh, people
like us do things like this.
Like people who live in this
neighborhood recycle on Tuesday
nights.
I guess we need to sign up for
recycling.
And there are really almost an
infinite range of examples that
are like that, both large
and small, where our habits are
, we notice them because the
people around us are doing
them, which is what the Q
portion is you referenced.
We desire to do them.
We crave to follow through on
them because by doing the same,
we fit in or signal to
the other people around us, Hey
, I get it.
I'm part of the tribe too.
It becomes easier to do it
because sometimes you have
friends helping you out, you
know,
like it's like having a spotter
at the gym.
Like, Oh, people like us to
help each other out when a set
is hard.
And then ultimately it becomes
satisfying because you enjoy
being praised for it.
You know, other people are like
, Hey, it was great to see you
at church on Sunday or, you
know, really good job on that
workout today.
And that feels good to be
praised for fitting in.
And so in that way, socially
reinforced habits or the
collective identity, it hits
all four
stages of habit formation.
And I knew that when I was
writing it, but I don't think I
gave it as much importance
as I should have.
It's a very powerful driver of
behavior in the long run.
Yeah, totally.
And I think this is why cyn
icism is such a toxic attitude.
And you know, I'm, I guess I'm
in Gen X.
I'm born in 1980.
There's a lot of cynicism in
Gen X.
And then millennials also have
a little bit of this too.
And I think, and actually to be
honest, everybody has it.
Baby boomers have it when, you
know, if you're a 50 year old
programmer and you're, you get
hired at a startup where the
CEO is 20 years old, we kind of
default to cynicism.
And it, it, it's such a blocker
when you're like trying to
observe those norms like, Oh
wait, like people like us do
things like this.
Cynicism allows you to go, well
, yeah, people like that do
stuff like that.
That's good for them.
That's good for James Clear.
But you know, that's not good
for me.
And when I'm trying to kind of
reveal from my experience for
anyone that ever watches
this or listens to this is that
you really do need to step
outside that and at least
be open to this idea that your
life could get better.
And it could just be going,
okay, well, I'm going to, I'm
going to vote for who I'm going
to be today and I'm going to
vote for who I'm going to be
tomorrow and I'm going to
keep going.
The other thing in the book
that really helped me and I'll
probably butcher it so you
clean
up after I do it, but you show
this grid.
So imagine like on this side of
your day, it's like, okay, I
make a good decision.
So it goes up.
And then I make another good
decision.
It goes up.
But then I make a bad decision.
Like I eat a tub of ice cream
and you know, sometimes eating
the tub of ice cream is like
debilitating.
It's like, well, I'm done.
I ate the tub of ice cream.
I suck at this.
I'm just going to go get into
bed and forget about it.
And in your grid, you show,
wait, but you're still up here.
Like you can just make another
good decision and then you're
back up again.
And I like that idea of kind of
navigating your ideas, not
being so hard on ourselves.
Did I kind of get that right?
Yeah.
So this is the, I don't know if
you can see it, but this is the
image.
But it's, it's a, it's this
idea that like the difference
between a good day and a bad
day is often just a series of
choices, right?
And you can win each little
moment, right?
You can win each decisive
moment just because you ate the
tub of ice cream doesn't mean
you can't win the next moment.
And, and so one thing that I
was thinking about when I wrote
that is this concept that
I call decisive moments.
This idea that there are a few
choices each day, maybe
somewhere between say five and
10 that kind of determine the
next chunk of time.
And so, so for example, there's
a moment for me each morning
where I sit down and either
I open up Evernote and I start
writing the next start.
I'll call, I'm going to work on
, or I go to ESPN and I check
the latest sports news.
And what happens in the next
hour is really determined by
what happens in like the first
45 seconds.
You know, like, do I, do I go
to Evernote or do I go to ESPN?
And so that is a decisive
moment in my language.
That's like a moment that
determines if I can master
those 45 seconds, then I can
end
up mastering the next hour that
comes afterward almost
automatically.
Same thing is true.
There's a moment each night,
like 515 or so, my wife gets
home from work and either we
change into our workout clothes
, or we like sit on the couch
and watch reruns the office
and order Indian food or
whatever.
And both of those nights are
good nights, but the moment to
master is do we change into
our workout clothes or not?
If we do that, it only takes a
few minutes.
Everything else for the next
two hours is already decided.
We'll get in the car, we'll
drive to the gym, we'll do the
reps, like it's all, it's all
pretty much done at that point.
So the reason I like bringing
that up or like thinking about
that is you start to really
realize there really isn't that
much that you need to master.
Really you just are trying to
focus your attention on a few
key decisive moments throughout
the day.
It's kind of like applying judo
to your life.
It's like apply the pressure
and the leverage at just the
right point and then the next
hour kind of falls into place
automatically.
And so I like that because once
you realize that, once you kind
of identify those high
leveraged decision points, you
can organize your day and your
environment around those
things.
If I know that those 45 seconds
where I'm choosing between E
vernote or ESPN is a real
key moment, well, I could
install freedom and then I
could block ESPN from 8am to 10
am
and that takes care of that
decisive moment and it
increases the odds that I'm
going to
open it instead.
But anyway, so little choices
like that are easier to make
once you've identified some
of those key points of leverage
.
Yeah, and you talk in the book
like there's some tricks to
where you can make things
automatic.
You talk about Nira y'all
buying a little device that
just shuts off his internet
every
night at 10am.
Yeah, yeah, outlet timer.
Yeah, and what's brilliant
about that is like it shuts it
off, like especially if it's in
the basement or whatever, like
you're not going to go
downstairs and like fiddle
around
with it and then it's just,
that's what happens, right?
If ESPN was really killing you,
you could just cancel your
cable subscription, that
might be a bit, but then you go
to watch ESPN, you can't, right
?
It's done.
By the way, you mentioned this
in the book too, but it's so
funny how certain people's,
it is a trigger for some people
is not for others.
Like ESPN for me is not a, that
's not a temptation at all.
Yeah, it doesn't even enter
your worldview.
Doesn't enter my worldview, but
it shows you how identity is so
much a part of this.
If I was hanging out with a
bunch of Oilers fans every
single day, and this happened
in
the co-work office, there's a
few people and they're watching
Oilers games on their computers
,
but I realized like if I want
to talk to them, I've got to
start watching Oilers games.
So people like us do things
like this.
And so I started developing
this habit of watching Oilers
games when, before I didn't
even care.
I think that, I mean, I think
this is one of the reasons why
sports is so tribal, why
people get so emotional about
it, is that it becomes a
connection point for the
relationships.
It's not even, the game is
actually, no one would ever say
that because everybody acts
like the game is the thing that
matters the most.
But in a weird way, it's kind
of a secondary thing.
Really, like when I think back
for me, sports is a way for my
brother and I to connect and
for us to have something to
text about and chat about
throughout the week.
It's a thing that, it's a
reason for my dad and I to get
together in person and to go
to games and hang out.
And like it's all the other
stuff that it provides that
makes it so deeply meaningful.
And then you end up assigning a
lot of that emotion to how the
team does on the field
as well, you know, the scores
on the scoreboard.
But yeah, it's a good example
there.
On that topic then, and this is
Corey Stone is asking this in
chat, but there's a lot
of people on Twitter that ask
this too.
Given that example that you
just gave, if your meaningful
relationships are engaging in
habits that might not be good
for you or that you want to
change, how do you navigate
that?
So if you're really feeling
like I got to stop watching
sports, it's just like I get
a little bit and then I just go
crazy, but I still want to have
a relationship with my
brother.
This is where it gets complex,
especially if you're married to
somebody.
If your wife is at least
somewhat inclined to want to go
to the gym, I'm guessing.
But if she was like, no, I just
want to watch Netflix and order
Indian food.
That's all I want to do.
How do you start to navigate
those things?
Yeah, those are good questions.
I mean, it's really hard
because especially if it's a
person who you want to stay in
your
life, you know, I think first
of all, I just want to say, so
I have some things I want
to add to this, but I feel like
it's worth noting that this
question comes up a lot.
And I think the reason it comes
up a lot is because we all know
that actually there isn't
a good, easy answer and that it
's like just a hard part of life
.
You know what I mean?
Like everybody wants, it's one
of those things we want to keep
asking about in hopes that,
oh, maybe there'll be an easy
way to resolve this.
But I think we all know like it
's a challenge.
Now that said, there are a few
things you can do.
So first thing is sometimes
your friends and family want to
do something different than
how you want to change.
So like you want to stick to a
new diet, they want to eat the
old way or something like
that.
So you want to start doing yoga
, they couldn't care less about
yoga.
They don't want to go to class
with you.
Things like that.
Well, if that's the case, then
for certain habits, you don't
have to like fire your friends
and family to be able to do
that.
But what you can, what you do
need or what can be really
useful is having like a sacred
space where that occurs where I
'm not saying you need to do
this with me, but just don't
make it harder on me, right?
Just don't conflict with.
So the yoga example is an
easier one where it's like,
well, maybe you need to go to a
yoga studio away from the
friends and family that aren't
interested and start to build
friendships with people who are
.
I'm not saying you need to get
rid of your old friends, but
maybe it'd be helpful to
build a couple of new ones who
are into yoga so that you have
like a safe space for that
habit to live.
So that's one thing.
Then there's the second piece,
which is sometimes you're
building a habit that you do
want the
person to like join you on to
come along with you.
You're working out and you
would love for your spouse to
join you at the gym or
something
like that.
Everybody know it like it would
be good, but maybe they feel
less comfortable there than
you do.
Or maybe they feel you were
previously an athlete and they
were not.
And so you feel kind of
comfortable in the gym.
You've been there before in
years past, but for them it's
like new and weird and they
feel
like they're being judged and
whatever.
If you're dealing with a case
like that, the thing that I try
to keep in mind and I can
tell you from working with my
own family, it can be
incredibly useful is praise the
good ignore the bad.
It's very hard to do.
It's very the difficult part
about it is not doing it on an
individual basis.
It's that this needs to be the
new lifestyle for you.
So when they do the thing that
you're asking them to do, don't
basically another way to
phrase this is don't criticize
people for doing what you were
hoping they would.
There are so many times when
the introverted kid in the
family will come down to the
dinner
table and it's like, oh, look
who decided to join us.
It's like, well, they finally
did the thing that you were
hoping they would do and engage
with everybody.
And now they just feel like
they're getting criticized for
it.
Or you go to the gym and your
spouse decides to join you and
they do a few sets and then
they feel like they're done.
And you say, well, that was a
pretty short workout.
And what you should be saying
is I think it's great that you
got in here tonight, right?
Like you weren't feeling it,
but you were still able to make
it in.
And so praise the good ignore
the bad.
And if you can do that in the
long run, what ends up
happening is everybody likes
feeling
praised.
Everybody likes feeling
rewarded.
It feels satisfying to do
something that the people who
love you and who are around you
praise you for.
And so at first you go to the
gym and they say, hey, I'm
really proud of you for getting
in here tonight.
Good job.
And it doesn't seem like much.
But then after two months and
three months and 10 months of
that, you turn around a year
later and they might never even
say it.
But implicitly what they've
realized is, damn, every time I
go to the gym, it feels good.
They compliment me.
And that so now all of a sudden
you start to associate going to
the gym with feeling
good.
And this is a really long game
play because it takes a while
for that to reinforce itself.
But same thing like the intro
verted kid at the table sits
down and they say something
that happened today.
And it's like, oh, that's
awesome.
Thanks for sharing that with us
.
And like on that individual
night, that one night at dinner
doesn't count for a lot.
But if every time they speak up
, they're rewarded for it, then
all of a sudden now they have
a reason to start doing that
more in the months and years to
come.
So it takes a while.
But I think that that's like an
effective way to gradually n
udge people in the right
direction.
Yeah.
There's someone in the chat
that's saying they need to
apply that idea to themselves
to avoid feeling guilty for not
doing enough.
So instead of reinforce, oh,
you idiot, you didn't go to the
gym again.
You fatty.
You know, like that's not
helpful.
Because the self talk, it can
work with self talk as well.
This is why I think small
habits can be so useful in some
ways, even on the bad days,
because like, let's say you're
in that situation you just said
where it's like, oh, you know,
skip the gym again.
Yeah.
Well, you can still do one push
up or one air squat or whatever
before you go do a set
of 10 air squats before you hop
in bed tonight.
And it's not going to transform
your body, but that's not
really the point.
The point is to prove to
yourself that it wasn't a good
day.
I didn't have the best
motivation or energy.
I had a long day at work, but I
still am not the type of person
who misses workouts.
I still proved to myself.
I still cast a vote for being
that kind of person.
I didn't let a day go by
without doing nothing.
And that can count for a lot in
the long run.
And so sometimes small habits
are less about the outcome they
deliver and more about the
identity they reinforce.
Yeah.
So I actually found, you know,
another thing I tried to, I'm
implementing in the new year
is I decided to quit drinking
alcohol.
And right now it's ostensibly
for this goal of hitting a
revenue mark once I hit the
goal,
then I can have a drink.
But the deeper motivation for
me was I just realized like it
just makes, it's a depressant.
It's like there's a bunch of
reasons that it's not good for
me.
And so my excuse or my way of
trying it out is saying, well,
I'm going for this goal.
But it's been interesting in
social situations because all
my friends still drink and that
's
fine with me.
But sometimes just sharing the
goal, oh, I'm just doing this
because I'm going after this
thing.
And you talk about how goals
are sometimes helpful in
setting your direction, you
know,
like, okay, I'm pointed this
way now.
And sometimes sharing that with
people is helpful.
The other thing is, I think
eventually if I just keep doing
this, just for me to say,
well, I'm a non-drinker now.
And so I can still go and have
my favorite, and it's also nice
having a thing that you
like.
So my favorite non-alcoholic
drink is a non-alcoholic Caesar
.
It's like a Bloody Mary.
And to have that drink, it's
like kind of spicy.
There's a reward there.
I also have this social crutch
that I can use in a situation,
you know.
And if somebody asks me about
it, I also have this new
identity, which is, oh, I'm a
non-drinker
now.
I just don't drink.
And you talked about that.
There's some research behind
that.
I know you've mentioned it a
lot, but it's like I'm trying
to quit smoking versus I'm
a non-smoker, right?
Is that correct?
Correct, right?
Yeah.
So I think that can be really
helpful.
Yeah.
Having, I think what you're
explaining here, the situation
that you're going through, this
experience you're having, is
kind of, it's illustrating this
process of identity change,
right?
It started with, oh, I'm just
going to put it off for a
little while while I'm
attacking
this goal.
But then you're casting so many
votes for like, you know what,
I haven't drank and like,
I'm kind of benefiting from it.
Like maybe this is part of my
identity now.
Maybe I'm a non-drinker.
And so anyway, yeah, I think
you're definitely on the right
track there.
Yeah.
And actually, this is a good
time to bring up two Twitter
questions.
Maria Aldry asks, you know, how
do you maintain habits?
Ask him about maintaining
habits for people with
depression, anxiety, or
attention deficit.
Do you want to try to tackle
that?
Yeah.
So I've tried to be careful
about saying that atomic habits
is about building habits and
breaking bad habits, building
good ones.
But it's not a book on
addiction.
It's not a book on depression.
It's not a book about anxiety
or ADHD or any of these other
disorders or ailments.
And I don't consider myself an
expert on addiction.
However, something interesting
has happened.
So I published the book and I
have had a ton of speaking
requests recently.
And so I've been doing speeches
at conferences and companies
and different events and
whatever.
And so many times, I get
someone that comes up to me
afterward or that asks a
question
during Q&A that talks about how
useful the book was for their
son who had ADHD or their
cousin was a meth addict and
then was able to like start to,
you know, write the ship
by employing some of these
techniques or whatever.
Yeah.
Which is great, which is very
gratifying.
I still stand by my original
statement.
I'm not an expert on addiction.
I don't want to like take a
strong stance with this stuff.
But what I've realized is that
the principles that I lay out
in atomic habits are really
about how human behavior works.
It's about how habits are
formed.
And whether that habit is
something extreme, like an
addiction or picking your skin
or
OCD or ADHD or whatever, or
whether it's something more
moderate like meditating for
three minutes
a day.
The fundamentals tend to be
similar.
And so I'm not going to say
that the book offers a
prescription for overcoming add
ictions.
But what I will say is you'd be
hard pressed to find tactics in
the book that wouldn't
at least help, right?
They wouldn't at least nudge
people in the right direction.
I have heard from a few readers
who specifically have said that
they had ADHD and they found
the book very helpful.
Environment design for whatever
reason has been something that
's come up multiple times
for folks who have struggled
with that.
So I think it's kind of like if
you're the type of person who
is less likely to just
remember to do it, right?
Or just follow your to-do list.
If that's not you, then struct
uring an environment where it's
easier to see the cues of your
good habits, less likely to see
the distractions, less friction
between you and the good
behavior,
more friction between you and
the bad ones.
If you place yourself in that
space, it's much more likely
that you're going to fall
through.
You know, those are things that
I talk about in chapters 6 and
12.
But I think that the book
applies, but I don't pitch it
as like a prescription for
someone
dealing with a more serious
issue.
Totally.
Yeah, and I would say, again, I
'm not an expert either, but as
someone who has been dealing
with depression the past couple
years, having a professional
that you go to that deals with
this stuff all the time like a
therapist is so helpful.
And the therapist will be very
interested if you read James'
book.
So I said to my therapist, I'm
like, you know, she starts way
back here.
And then she says, "So what's
new with you?"
I'm like, "Well, you know, I
read this book and I'm thinking
, oh, what are you thinking
about doing with that?"
"Oh, I'm thinking about maybe
quitting alcohol."
"Oh, well, that's, you know,
there's some reinforcement from
the professionals."
And likewise with my doctor,
you know, when I had depression
and I went to my physician,
she said, she gave me two pres
criptions, quit drinking alcohol
and quit taking any kind
of cannabis.
And the reason is she says, "
Those are going to make you feel
bad."
Now the trigger in that case
was my doctor.
It's nice when you have a
doctor saying, "Listen, this is
your prescription."
Oh, and double the amount of
exercise I was doing.
So three things.
Those, so I did that for three
months and then, you know, I
went back to my old habits.
But now I have that memory of
what it was like for three
months and it's been a powerful
trigger for me to, you know,
when I am starting to notice my
mood go down, I can, I
remembered,
you know, my doctor's
prescription was quit drinking,
quit, you know, eating edibles
and
doubling my exercise.
And that's been helpful for me
personally.
So I think if you're reading
the book, let your professional
in your life know about
it.
It's good.
And one thing I want you to do
is, because I love the imagery,
but, and this is probably
unfair to you, is to give the
ice cube example, but use
Celsius instead of Fahrenheit.
So this is an example from the
first chapter of the book.
And I actually, as a side note,
I thought about this.
I was like, man, we're going to
have to get these changed for
the foreign editions.
Like we're going to, it's going
to need to be, but anyway, so.
Yeah, I think you can do that.
Yeah.
The core idea is that the
process of changing your habits
is, well, it's similar to what
we talked about early on, that
there's often this valley of
death, that there's this period
where you're just kind of
building up latent potential,
but you're not really releasing
any other results yet.
And I like to equate it to the
process of heating up an ice
cube.
So you've got this ice cube
sitting on a table.
And so let's say it's like
negative three degrees in there
.
So you're at negative three, it
's cold, you can see your breath
, the ice cube's sitting
there, you heated up negative
two, negative one.
Still, there's this ice cube
sitting there.
Nothing has happened.
Then you go from negative one
to zero.
And all of a sudden, you have
this one degree shift, no
different than any of the other
shifts that came before it, but
you have this phase transition,
right?
And like the ice cube starts
melting.
And that I think is indicative
of what it often feels like to
change a habit.
You're making these little
improvements, you're trying to
make these 1% changes, these
one
degree shifts each day.
And you're like, it's really
easy to get frustrated or even
depressed at that point.
You know, it's like, I've been
running for three weeks, how
come I can't see a change
in my body?
Or I've been writing blog posts
for six months now, how come
this site isn't popular yet?
And the key point there is your
work was not being wasted, it's
just being stored.
Complaining about sticking to a
habit for two months or three
months or even six months
or a year and not having the
outcome that you want is kind
of like complaining about
heating an ice cube from
negative three to negative one
degrees and not melting it.
The work was not wasted, it's
just being stored.
And I love that quote that's in
that same section from Jacob
Reese, who it hangs in
the locker room of the San
Antonio Recruitment, won five
NBA championships.
And it says essentially, when I
feel like giving up, I think
about the stone cutter
who continues to hammer away at
the stone a hundred times
without it splitting.
And then finally, on the 101st
blow, it cracks in two.
And I know that it wasn't the
hundred that can't there.
I know it wasn't the 101st
swing that did it, but the
hundred that came before.
And like it's that same idea.
You know, the reason the site
takes off is not because of the
one viral article, it's
because of the 55 that you
wrote in the weeks and months
prior.
The reason that you see a
change in your body is not
because today's workout
radically
transform you, it's because you
've been sticking to it for
eight months now.
And it's really about showing
up, continue to put those
swings in, continue to raise
the temperature by one degree.
And eventually you hit that
phase transition where you can
see the results of your work.
Yeah.
And that image has been so
powerful in my life.
The re like I've been telling
people about this book and I
actually notice there's kind
of like a coffee shop test.
Like if I hear people talking
about something from Internet
culture in a coffee shop, like
real people, then something's
hit and atomic habits is like
that.
Like it hit the kind of
mainstream and that image of
just raising the temperature a
little
bit every day.
Now I feel like I'm a few
months into this and I'm a
little bit kind of like
evangelical
about it.
And now I'm like, God, like my
life is so much better.
And it's because of just these
little changes over time in the
same direction.
I can now I can see it.
Now I can see that I feel
better.
You know, wow, man, quitting
alcohol.
That was one thing.
And then wow, showing up at the
gym three or four times a week,
that really helps.
And wow, like reading a real
book every night before I go to
bed.
All of these things keep kind
of adding up and do make a
meaningful difference in your
life.
Even though way back when when
you're starting, you feel like,
well, nothing's going to help
me now.
It's I want to be clear that
this these ideas have meaning
fully impacted my life.
So I'm yeah, I'm really
thankful.
I'm thankful you wrote that
book.
I'm thankful you you talked to
me in the airport.
It's been really great for me.
That's awesome.
Thank you so much for sharing
that.
And ultimately, that's what the
whole thing is for, right?
I mean, it just it makes it
feel like it was worth the
effort to spend a few years
writing
it and working on it.
So that's great.
And so before you go, some
people are asking like what
recommendations for system
services,
tools, trackers.
I know you have a new one
coming out.
Do you want to talk about that?
Sure.
Yeah.
So I got it right here next to
me, actually.
So this is a habit journal.
And we we just launched it two
weeks ago.
And it's got it's basically a
dot grid notebook.
So if you're into bullet journ
aling or you're into keeping a
notebook or use a notebook,
the vast majority of it are dot
grid pages.
So you'll be able to use it
like any normal one.
But then at the back, there's a
section with a habit tracker
templates.
And I don't know if you can see
that very well, but I've been
using it.
For example, this is this month
.
So you can see me tracking my
habits on here.
And so anyway, those templates
are in the back and they're
also perforated.
So you can tear them out and
put them on your desk or put
them on your kitchen counter or
your refrigerator or whatever.
And then and then at the very
beginning of the book, there is
a section called one line
per day.
So I've been using it for what
happened today.
And so I've been writing down
what happened each day.
And there are 31 lines.
So one for each day of the
month.
And there are 12 of them.
So by the time you get to the
end of the year, you should be
able to flip through and see
if you I'm doing what happened
today, Sean Blanc, it does what
's the highlight of the
day.
Some other ones that I've seen
are what am I grateful for?
Or you could use it as like a
productivity thing.
You could say like, what's my
most important task today?
Things like that.
So there are a lot of examples
in the back of the notebook who
I have like 16 pages of
examples of how to use it.
But anyway, it's called the
habit journal.
And yeah, I'm excited about it.
I think it'll be a good tool to
help people build better habits
.
And a lot of folks, I've heard
from a lot of folks that really
like the audiobook.
So if you folks aren't readers,
go check out the audiobook.
People like us read atomic
habits.
So thanks again for your time,
James.
Really appreciate it, man.
Awesome.
Thank you.
There you go.
That was helpful for you.
Like I said, I really recommend
the book, Atomic Habits.com.
That journal that he's talking
about is also available there.
Folks, it's 2019.
And if you are tired of boot
strapping alone, I've been
running an online community,
especially
for bootstrapers, solopreneurs,
indie makers, and it's called
Mega Maker Club.
Go to megamaker.co/club.
If you want more information,
it's not open right now, but
you can sign up for the waiting
list.
And I will talk to you next
episode.
Thanks for listening.
Podcast hosting is provided by
transister.fm.
They host our MP3 files,
generate our RSS feed, provide
us with analytics, and help us
distribute the show to Spotify,
Apple Podcasts, and more.
If you want to start your own
podcast or you want to switch
to transistor, go to transister
.fm/justin
and get 15% off your first year
.
[MUSIC PLAYING]
(upbeat music)