Narrator: This is Transistor fm.
Justin Jackson:
Hey, product people.
Justin Jackson here, and I've
got a brand new interview for
you with James Clear, who is
the author of Atomic Habits, a
book that has really changed my
life, uh, since I've read it.
And I, I don't want to give
too much of an intro, I
just wanna get right into
the, the actual interview.
Uh, if you like this,
please reach out to James
on Twitter at James Clear.
And if you have comments
about the episode, reach
out to me on Twitter.
I'm the letter M, the
letter I, Justin m i Justin.
Here is me and James talking about
habits and how you can make your
life better one day at a time.
The book, your book's
been out for a while.
It's right here to habits.
If you see it in an airport
or something near you, how
long has it been out now?
James Clear: Uh, today
is a hundred days.
Exactly.
No way.
So yeah, so just, uh, just
over three months, you
Justin Jackson: know, I'm,
I'm curious 'cause now
it's been out for a while.
Is there one idea that you
see that people keep sharing?
Like one idea that resonated
from the book in particular, that
gets shared more than anything
else on Twitter or wherever?
Um,
James Clear: so I, I was
curious about that myself when
I was, you know, writing the
book and thinking about it
because I, I kind of felt like.
All right.
You know, hopefully all
these ideas are useful, but
what's the one thing that
people are gonna latch onto?
Because sometimes you'll hear
that from authors that like,
there was one chapter or
something that was the chapter
that really stuck with people.
Yeah.
Um, I'm grateful for the
fact that there are a variety
of things, but the, there,
um, there are a few things.
So the first one is identity-based
habits, which is chapter two.
Yeah.
Um, and that concept,
it really seems to have
resonated with people.
The idea of like trying to
reinforce your desired identity
and kind of like starting with
who you wanna become rather
than what you want to achieve.
Yes.
And, uh, I'm glad that it did,
because that was the chapter
I debated over the most of
where to put it in the book.
I had it, it it at
different points.
It was the first chapter.
It was the last chapter.
It ended up being the second one.
I also had this a thought in
my head that it should be like
about midway through the book.
So it really jumped
all over the place.
But I ended up thinking, I feel
like this is one of the best
ideas, so I want to have it
early so that people, even if
they don't finish the book, they
still come across this idea.
Yeah.
And I'm glad that, uh, that,
that ended up working out well.
Um, the other one that,
uh, people bring up a lot
is the two minute rule.
Um, and the idea of like scaling
your habits down to the point where
they take two minutes or less.
I think that that's like
a very actionable one.
You know, it's like, okay,
I know exactly what to do.
I wanted to do a workout,
but now I'll just focus
on doing five pushups.
Or I wanted to read 30 books
this year and now I'll focus
on reading one page a day,
or something like that.
Gotcha.
So I think the actionable of that
one also, uh, tends to stick.
Justin Jackson: And so going back
to the identity one, um, is this
the idea that every action you
take or every habit you develop
is a vote for the person you wanna
James Clear: become?
Right.
So that's kinda like my core,
um, philosophy behind it.
This idea that the way that
we develop beliefs about
ourselves, that we reinforce
our self-image, that we, uh,
develop our identity to a certain
degree, is largely reinforced
by the experiences and behaviors
that we perform over time.
Mm-hmm.
So some aspects of your
identity are relatively fixed.
Like for example, if you're
tall or short, but even that
idea that I am tall or I am
short, that's reinforced.
You learn that through
experiences in life.
Um, now there are many aspects
of your identity that are less
fixed than that, but are still
reinforced by your experiences.
So if you, you know, go, uh, if
you write one sentence today,
you probably don't think about
yourself as I'm a writer.
But if you do that every day for
six months or nine months, or a
year, At some point you turn around
and you think, huh, maybe I am the
kind of person who is a writer.
Yeah.
Or you know, if you, uh, if you
study biology every Tuesday night
for 20 minutes, like you at some
point think, I guess I'm studious.
You know, I keep
doing this every week.
Like maybe this is the
kind of person I am.
Yeah.
And so I like that idea that
our habits are like votes for
the, the type of person we
believe that we are, that they
build up evidence of looking
at ourselves in a certain way.
Mm-hmm.
And I like to phrase it that
way, not only 'cause I believe
that it's true, but also
like beliefs and behavior
are kind of a two-way street.
Right.
So like you can, you'll hear
people say things like, Well,
you know, just be positive
or just believe in yourself
or fake it till you make it.
Yeah.
Or things like that.
And there's nothing
necessarily wrong with
fake it till you make it.
Like it's, it's fine to be
positive and believe things about
yourself, but it's a very short
term strategy because fake it
till you make it is asking you to
believe something about yourself
without having evidence for it.
You know, it's like that kind
of visualization stuff or
mantra stuff where you look at
yourself in the mirror and you
tell yourself, I'm a writer.
I'm a writer.
Yeah.
Even though you
haven't written yet.
Um, and so what I'm
saying is similar, but.
I think importantly different
in the sense that you let
the behavior lead the way
rather than the belief.
And I, I think that's the best
lever we have for changing the way
that we look at ourselves, which
is to say, show up and write a
sentence every day and soon you're
gonna have something to root that
new identity of I am a writer in.
And it gives, it's a much more,
I think, robust and long-term
way of changing how you look at
Justin Jackson: yourself.
Yeah.
I think for me, the 'cause you
first communicated that idea
to me in an airport in Denver.
James Clear: Yeah, I remember
Justin Jackson: that.
And the, at the time in my
life, I was not doing so good.
I was, uh, depressed.
I was, I think cynical, especially,
I think cynical about people
like you that seem to have
it all together, that seem
to have, be really like doing
all the, the, the good habits.
And when you're not doing so good.
Looking at someone that, you know,
seems to have it all together,
just can make you more grumpy or
more cynical, or more whatever.
But I remember you sitting down
and, and kind of hashing this out
with me and that idea of Justin, no
matter where you're at right now,
and no matter what you've done, you
could start today with one action.
So if you, you know, go
running today, that might
not make a big difference.
But then if you do it tomorrow
and then the next day, and then
the next day, and then the next
day at the end of the week, you
might say, well wait a second.
I, I think I'm a runner, right?
And maybe, you know, after a couple
weeks you might say, well, you
know, I'm gonna get myself some
runner clothes and go and get some
runner clothes, and then I'm gonna
get myself a good pair of shoes.
I'm gonna install that Strava app.
Hmm.
And all of a sudden
you could see yourself.
That was very, that was a really
hopeful message for me when I was
really struggling to figure out.
It was way easier for me to be
cynical and just kind of look back
at all these people implementing
good, healthy processes and
say, well, that's not for me.
That's just for people
that, whatever, you know.
But seeing, hearing that
gave me hope to think,
you know, I could do that.
I could.
And it's surprising how little
time it takes to mm-hmm.
You know, accomplish that.
Is that something?
Ha ha.
Have other people been
kinda referencing that too?
Is that part of the, the, and
maybe that's what's so good about
having it as chapter two, because
it gives me some hope, right?
Yeah.
Well,
James Clear: what's interesting is
that that process of changing in
that way, it's happening anyway.
You know, like, I mean, if
you think back to like the
beginning, like for example, if
I think of my, the early days
of my entrepreneurial career.
Mm-hmm.
Well, I didn't have any
entrepreneurs in my family.
I didn't have any close
friends who were entrepreneurs.
There was no reason for me to think
that's who I am or to feel like
I was externally validated with,
like, that was part of my identity.
Yeah.
I had no evidence of it.
And so early on I just,
all I had was hope.
Right?
Like the hope that, oh, maybe
I'll be able to build something.
Maybe I'll be able
to make this work.
Yeah.
Um, but then you start to show up
and for me it was probably about
two years in, it's probably about
where the, where I kind of like
the scale tipped and I started
to think I am an entrepreneur.
Like that's part of, of who I
am, but it really took proving
it to myself that I can pay my
bills through this, you know,
that I can like actually have a
lifestyle and a career in this way.
Yeah.
I had to prove it for about
two years before I really
started to latch onto it
and say, this is who I am.
Yeah.
Um, and, uh, so my point
is that's always happening.
You're, you're always,
you're continually updating
your beliefs about yourself
based on the experiences
that you're going through.
Yeah.
And all I'm talking about is simply
designing that process in a little
more careful or thoughtful way,
rather than just kind of letting
it happen to you and be like, well,
I guess I'll figure out who I am
based on what life throws at me.
Yes.
Versus.
How about I figure out who I am
based on the votes that I cast
each day and what I decide to,
what habits I decide to follow.
Justin Jackson: Yeah.
Yeah.
Again, like that is a, a very
hopeful message for, for someone
who's just kind of sitting back
and waiting for it to happen.
Um, what, what sustains
you when you're in the.
In the process, but not there yet.
Hmm.
Like, like you mentioned
entrepreneur and you're like,
man, it took a long time.
Yeah.
James Clear: What sustaining,
that's a really good question
because I think a lot of habits,
you know, entrepreneurship is
certainly this way, exercise is
this way where the, the rewards
of a habit are often very delayed.
Uh, you know, like what's
the reward for working
out for like three weeks?
Like, not really a
whole lot, honestly.
Your body hasn't really changed.
The scale is probably
about the same.
Um, you're probably
just sore, you know?
Yeah.
Like, there, there probably isn't
like a whole lot to show for it.
Yeah.
It's really not, unless you
stick with that habit for
three months or six months or
a year, that you actually start
to see the changes you were
hoping to get when you set out.
Yeah.
And so there's kind of this like
valley of death in the beginning.
Mm-hmm.
Where.
In a way, it's sort of
like gets harder before
it gets easier, you know?
It feels uncomfortable.
You feel sore and pain,
uh, you feel uncertain
when you walk in the gym.
You feel like people
are judging you.
Yeah.
Same way with starting a business,
you know, in a weird way it's kind
of harder before it gets easier.
You start out, but you're
not making any money.
You feel stupid a lot of the
time 'cause you're, you don't
know how to make a sales call
or what customers are looking
for or whether you're even
offering the right product.
Yeah.
Um, I remember when I first
started, I, uh, I, like I said,
I didn't know anybody, didn't
have any entrepreneurs in my
family, so I was like, well, I
need to get to know some people.
Yeah.
So I sent a bunch of emails
to reach out and just ask if
people would chat on Skype for
like 30 minutes or whatever.
And I remember sending those
first few and thinking, is this
even, do people even do this?
Do people chat on Skype with people
that they haven't met before?
Like, is this a weird thing to ask?
You know, there's just a lot
of that uncertainty early on.
Yeah.
So your point is, I think, a
valid one, which is, well, what
do you do to get through that?
You know, like how do you,
how do you kind of get
through that valley of death
while you're waiting for the
long-term rewards to accumulate?
Yeah, and I think that this is
where, uh, psychologists call
it reinforcement or an external
reinforcer, but you, you want
some kind of reinforcement that is
enjoyable in the moment so that you
have a reason to keep showing up.
Okay.
So there are, there are kind of,
from a habit standpoint, there
are kind of two ways to do this.
First thing is just a strategic
choice about what type of
habit you choose to follow.
So if we go back to the exercise
example, well not everybody has
to work out like a bodybuilder.
You know, you could do
Pilates or yoga or go for a
run or rock climbing or, you
know, all kinds of stuff.
Yeah.
And so pick the form of a habit
that brings you the most joy
that is most enjoyable to you.
Yeah.
It's gonna be a slog for,
you know, you're gonna
have to swim for months to
see a change in your body.
You're gonna have
to cycle for months.
You're gonna have to
lift weights for months.
It doesn't really matter
which one you choose.
It's gonna take a while.
Yeah.
So you might as well choose
the one that's most exciting
or enjoyable to you.
Yeah.
Um.
Yeah, same way with like, you
know, imagine a reading habit,
you know, like you don't have
to read, you might feel like,
oh, I have a business so I
need to read business books.
But really, ultimately the most
important thing is do you get
in the habit of reading, do
you fall in love with reading?
Yeah.
So if you need to start with sci-fi
books or fantasy or something
like that, well start with that.
You know, like do do the one that
is, uh, intrinsically valuable to
you at first, and once the habit
is built, then you can transition
to some of the other stuff.
Yeah.
Um, so that's one method for,
for kind of getting through that
Justin Jackson: value of death.
Yeah.
And I think this brings up maybe
a harder question, which is, so,
you know, based on your book,
it's January and I'm thinking,
okay, you know, I haven't been
in the gym for seven years.
I used to love working out.
I'm gonna go, I.
I got my streaks app on my
phone, start going, and, uh, I've
probably been, I don't know, I've
probably been at least 18 days,
or maybe even 20 days this month.
So it's great.
And I was surprised
by how fast I felt.
So the first day I felt like
I didn't belong, felt awkward.
I don't know anybody here.
I'm walking in, I, some
of the machinery, I, I
recognize some, I don't.
I have to like, you know,
find, get back into a routine.
I have to find which
exercise I'm gonna do.
There's all these kind of
insecurities and questions.
But after a week, I kind
of felt like I belonged.
Hmm.
But I wonder if that's
because it was easier for me.
You know, I, I had this, you
know, I'm, I'm relatively, I
was already relatively in shape.
Um, so there's a big difference
between going in where you feel
like, oh, maybe I'm a few pounds
overweight and going in and
being 200 pounds overweight.
There's a big difference between,
you know, going in even as a
white male compared to, you know,
the, there's a, a big difference
going in and feeling like, well,
I've done these exercises before,
so I'm not completely outta my
element, and I'm wondering how it.
I mean, are, are, are
habits like that achievable
because of privilege and
context and other things?
Like how much does
that play into it?
And, you know, if someone is
walking in and they're 200 pounds
overweight is, you know, do
they still have the same chance
of progress and successfully,
it just feels like such a
big mountain for them to go
James Clear: over.
For sure.
Yeah.
They're, um, so this is one
reason why I think starting with
small habits is so incredibly
important because a lot of the
time when we think about the
outcome that you want, so just
to continue your weight loss
or exercise example, yeah.
Everybody gets wrapped up in like,
oh, I wanna lose a hundred pounds,
or I wanna, you know, lose 20
pounds or whatever the number is.
Uh, but you forget about, they're
like all these little logistical
and emotional details that come
along with starting a new habit.
Yeah.
So, you know, I'll often tell the
story about, I have this reader
who he ended up losing over a
hundred pounds and, uh, one of the
first things he did was he went to
the gym, but he wasn't allowed to
stay for longer than five minutes.
So, okay.
He drove to the gym, got outta
the car, did half an exercise, got
back in the car, drove home, and
it sounds ridiculous to people.
It sounds silly because
it's like, well, clearly
exercising for five minutes
is not gonna get you in shape.
Like, that's not, but what you
realize is he was mastering
the art of showing up, right.
He was becoming the type of person
that drove to the gym every day.
Yeah.
And when you're in
that state, right.
For him, at that point, that
was the biggest shift was can
I, can I just become the type
of person who gets in here?
Right?
Who overcomes the uncertainty
or feeling uncomfortable
or feeling judged.
And all those things are very
real hurdles to building a habit.
You know, like there's, there
are all these little questions
that need to be answered
for something like that.
Like, okay, I want
to go to the gym.
Well, what time am I gonna go?
Am I gonna go before
work or after work?
Yeah.
What gym will I go to?
What route am I gonna
take to get there?
Do I need to bring a water bottle?
Or is there like a water
fountain at the gym?
Yeah.
And all those little questions
like that, like, you know,
whether or not you, uh, there's
a water fountain at the gym.
It sounds small, but if you
already feel uncomfortable and
feel like you don't belong, and
then you always forget to bring
your water bottle and you're
like, oh, there's nothing ever and
there's never anything to drink
there, that's enough friction to
get you to quit in the beginning.
Yeah.
So starting with
something simple like.
All I'm gonna do is I'm
gonna show up and I'm gonna
do one exercise for five
minutes and then I'm gonna go.
Mm-hmm.
Um, that I think is
a good way to start.
And it reminds me of what
Steven Pressfield wrote.
I think it was in the War of
Art, where he said something to
the effect of like, if you sit
down each day at the computer
and you do your writing, at
some point, at first it feels
uncomfortable, but at some point
that becomes your territory.
And I really like that phrasing
of it, because for an animal,
for a wolf or something, a,
a plate, a piece of land does
not become their territory
unless they spend time in it.
Mm-hmm.
Right?
Unless they're there each day.
Yeah.
It has to become comfortable first.
And so for many people building
habits, whether that's getting
into the gym or going to the yoga
studio, or sitting your butt in
the chair and writing, you need
to make that space your territory.
And at the very first step
is not getting a result.
It's spending time there.
Mm-hmm.
It's making that little bit of
land a zone where you feel like
this is where I belong each day.
Yeah.
And, uh, and that, that's a
big emotional hurdle to cross
before you even worry about
any of the physical or like
actual technical things to do.
Yeah.
Justin Jackson: Yeah.
And I mean, the other thing that
helped, uh, is I went with my wife
and, uh, it's funny 'cause I felt
like, you know, I'm like, uh, Mr.
Confident, but she, she was like,
at one point she's like, Justin,
you are so nervous right now.
Like, she could tell
how nervous I was.
And I thought I was like
keeping it all together.
And it just reminded me of
like, I'd been in gyms from
the time I was in grade nine
all the way through college.
It wasn't like it was
unfamiliar, but I was nervous.
Because I was unfamiliar.
I, there had been a seven year gap
and now I was like exploring this
again, worried about what these
people are, are thinking about me.
Wow, that guy looks like
he's way more fit than me.
You know, like all these
thoughts go through your head.
And so, um, yeah, I think kind
of figuring out how you can like,
make a step and sometimes maybe
it's like going with somebody so
you at least have some emotional,
'cause it's emotional, it's
nice to have someone to kind
of share the emotional burden.
James Clear: Right.
For sure.
Well, if you come, the thing that,
um, ultimately what you're looking
to do is, like we just said, feel
like it's part of your territory.
Yeah.
And because there are other people
in that space, what that also
means is you're looking to feel
like you're part of the tribe.
Yes.
Who goes there, right.
That you, you belong with the
other people who are in that room.
Yeah.
And, uh, so it helps to
What, what is a tribe?
Well, it's a group of people
that you get along with,
that you bond with, that you
belong to over something else.
Yeah.
Over some shared interest.
And in other words, it's a group
in a lot of ways of friends.
Friends who share
some kind of interest.
So these are your gym friends?
Yeah.
Well, If you go with your
wife, then you automatically
have at least one person in
the tribe that you are friends
with, that you do belong with.
Yeah.
Um, and so I think that helps you
get over that hurdle a little bit.
You're not, you're no longer
facing that challenge alone.
You know, before it was like,
I am trying to get fit now.
It is.
We are trying to get fit.
Yeah.
And, uh, that, that helps a lot
with the kind of the mental feeling
of like, do I belong or not?
Yeah.
Justin Jackson: I've also
found, sorry, I don't mean
to stay on this too long, but
it's so fresh that the other
thing I found myself doing,
because I'm interested in the
emotional friction behind habits.
Mm-hmm.
And so the other thing I was
doing is I was going in there
and I'm uncomfortable, so I'm
trying to act really tough,
but I'm not tough at all.
I'm like, but I'm, you know, when
people look at me, I'm kind of like
scowling when like, I'm not being
friendly, I'm not being myself.
And, um, I was thinking about that
and thinking like, when you're
kind of inward focused and you're
in a new environment and you're
trying to develop a new habit, but
you're inward focused, it really
is, um, it, it doesn't really help.
And so I had to kind of turn
that around and go, okay, I
gotta start being friendly.
I gotta start saying
hi to these people.
Mm-hmm.
Because if I wave at this person
and it feels good, like they,
they respond with a smile.
And that happens again next time.
And again, next time.
That's a little bit
of a reward for me.
That's gonna keep
me going to the gym.
But if I keep going here
with this like tough.
Scowl on my face.
I, you know, and it's hard 'cause
you feel, you, you feel like you
don't belong, you feel nervous
and it, you kind of default to
these old, these weird behaviors.
But I, and it took a little
bit of time, but I've realized,
okay, I gotta, now I gotta get
in the habit of, of smiling and
saying hello when I'm in the gym.
Not just being like in my
own zone and pretending I'm,
you know, somebody I'm not.
James Clear: Right.
Well that's one thing that
kind of helps you start to
belong with the rest or become
part of the rest of the tribe.
You know, like just a friendly
behavior helps you start to
develop friendships with some of
those other people that are there.
Yeah, there was a.
A study that I wanted to
cite in Atomic Habits, but
I could, I couldn't find it
to track it down, but I read
about it years ago where,
um, the Y M C A ran a survey.
Yeah.
And when they surveyed people
who were joining the gym.
Okay.
The thing that got them to
join were, uh, the different
classes offered the equipment
that was in the gym.
Basically facilities and
features were the things that
got people in for the first time.
Yeah.
But then when they surveyed
members who had been there for
over a year, the thing that
got people to stick, nobody
mentioned features or facilities.
Everybody mentioned friendships.
Yes.
And so the people who actually
stayed at the gym or kept their
membership were the ones who
ended up developing friendships
with other people there.
Yeah.
And I think you're right.
Ultimately, the thing that
gets you to come back is
like, do I enjoy coming here?
Does it mean I get to
see some of my friends?
Does it mean I get to hang
out with people I like or.
You know, uh, it's really
the sense of belonging
that gets habits to stick.
Um, and the, the action itself
is just kind of like something
that's happening along the
Justin Jackson: way.
Yes.
But there's a, a, a, a step before
that that we kind of skipped over,
which is like, how do you even
choose a habit in the first place?
Like how does, how does that
happen in the sense of I might
not know what's good for me, so
what, how does that come into this?
James Clear: Yeah.
Well there are a lot of ways to
answer that question, so I'll
just share a couple thoughts
that are, that come to mind.
So I.
The first thought that comes to
mind is this question from, uh,
I first heard from Seth Godin,
which I think is just a great
question, which is, what is it for?
Mm-hmm.
Um, and so this is a question
that we need to ask ourselves when
we're trying to build a new habit,
which is, what is this habit for?
What is the, what am I actually
trying to achieve here?
Mm-hmm.
Because the correct habit to
choose is very different based on
what your goals are, what you're
hoping to get as an outcome,
what kinda lifestyle you want.
Mm-hmm.
Um, and you know, so for
example, the habit of
making 20 sales calls a day.
Well, if what it's for is
to increase revenue and to
build a successful business,
that's a wonderful thing.
Mm-hmm.
If you hate making sales calls
and you wanna spend less time
working and more time with
your family, that could be
a terrible habit to build.
Yeah.
It just depends on what it's for.
So, uh, that's one question
to ask, but you are correct
that we often don't know, uh,
what we need in the moment.
Mm-hmm.
And I think part of that's
just a challenge of life and a
challenge of self-awareness and,
you know, knowing what you need.
But life is a very complex
system and so figuring out
the right thing for that is
sometimes it's just impossible
or too many moving parts.
Yeah.
So, uh, I tend to default
to two possible answers.
The first answer is we all
need things that are so boring
that we don't think about them,
but are incredibly important
for showing up each day.
Yeah.
So I.
Did you sleep eight hours?
Are you drinking enough water?
Are you spending a little bit
of time walking outside or
getting a little bit of sunlight?
Um, do you exercise consistently?
Whatever form is
interesting to you mm-hmm.
Um, are you spending some time
reading and soaking up new ideas?
Now, I'm not saying you have
to do all that stuff every day.
Yeah.
But my point is like, those
are things that most people
would be like, yeah, of
course you should sleep and
read more books and exercise.
Everybody knows that's good.
Yeah.
But your time is almost never
going to be wasted by making
sure you do one of those things.
Yeah.
Right.
It's a, it's a fundamental
that's worth spending time on.
That's worth coming back to.
That's worth reminding
yourself of even if you
aren't sure the ideal perfect
place to focus in your life.
Yeah.
So that's the first answer,
come back to the fundamentals.
The second answer
is, uh, more broad.
I can't, I can't be specific
with it 'cause it depends on
each person, but the broad
application is what I would
call broad funnel type filter.
So whenever you're trying to figure
out where to focus, you need a
really broad range of research.
Try to get as many options as
possible, then apply a really
tight, strict filter to it and
just focus on the one or two
best options that you found.
Okay.
So for example, I just finished,
uh, atomic Habits a few months
ago, so now I'm thinking,
should I write a second book?
If I should, what
should that be about?
You know?
Yeah.
And I don't know right now,
so I'm in the broad funnel
stage, so I wanna lay out
as many options as possible.
I wanna brainstorm
a thousand titles.
I wanna look at all the
top books on Amazon.
I wanna browse my best
performing tweets and see
if there's a possible thread
for a book idea in there.
Mm-hmm.
I wanna look everywhere I can and
just list all of that stuff in the
same spreadsheet, and maybe I got.
1200 ideas on there,
really broad funnel.
But then I need to apply
a very tight filter.
Is this something I'm interested
in enough to spend two or
three or four years working on?
Mm-hmm.
Is it a topic of broad
appeal to a general audience?
Are there gonna be a lot
of people that like this?
Yeah.
Is this something that people,
that I can actually turn
into something actionable?
You know, like, can people
use this in their daily life?
Is this a topic that has a lot of
stories that I could tell, right?
Can I actually make this
entertaining or, you know, LA
latch onto other interesting
stories to make the book readable?
Yes.
So, and you know, and those
are just some of the filters,
but there're my point is
that, You want some period
of very broad exploration.
And then once you have a lot of
options, you wanna really tighten
it down based on that question.
What is this for?
Yeah.
So in my case, the question
I'm using is, well, it's for
writing a good book, one that's
highly actionable, one that
sells a lot of copies, one that
people find useful and so on.
Yeah.
And um, so I think if you combine
that broad funnel type filter
strategy and that question of
what is it for that can maybe give
you some more specific answers.
Mm-hmm.
But even if you don't come up
with something good there, you can
always focus on the fundamentals.
Justin Jackson: Yeah.
And the other thing, when you
mentioned Seth Godin, uh, he has
this other line, which is People
like us do things like this.
James Clear: I love that line.
I wish I had thought
it up, but I Yeah.
Yeah.
It's so good.
Justin Jackson: It's such a
great like, mantra and it, what's
interesting about it is like,
for me, One thing that made me
start thinking about healthy
habits was hanging out with
people who had healthy habits.
Mm-hmm.
And, and in some ways it was
really lucky and fortunate,
like, um, you know, like, you
guys invited me to that retreat.
You dead.
Yep.
And in some ways I'm thankful
you guys invited a loser like me.
'cause I was like, I hanging
out in that group, you know,
I came and at first I was
cynical and grumpy and um, and
eventually, you know, just looking
around that group, I realized,
man, these people like this.
Do things like this and my
cynicism, which before would've
been like, wow, people like
that do stuff like that.
You know, it, it went down
and then all of a sudden I
was like, okay, well if people
like this, do things like
this, that's what I need to do.
And I think.
Uh, for folks that are, you know,
thinking like, okay, well how
do I know what good habits are?
There are so many things that
I would've never been, um, you
know, uh, what do you call it?
There's like the, there's the
stages of habits or whatever,
but I would've never even had the
cue if I had not first observed
it and then noticed like, oh
wait, they're doing that, they're
doing that, they're doing that.
I'm the odd man out.
Yeah.
And that's what motivated
me to want to, to pursue
some of that stuff.
But if I hadn't been in that
group and felt like, wait,
wait a second, like if I wanna
belong here, I gotta, I've
gotta, I gotta up my game.
Right?
Um, it would've never happened.
And so people like us do
things like this has been
really helpful for me.
James Clear: Yeah.
I love that phrase.
And one of the reasons I said
that, oh, I wish I had thought
that up, is because I think
it applies so deeply to a lot
of the ideas in atomic habits.
It applies to.
Um, how socially
reinforced our habits are.
Yeah.
I think this is, you know, I,
I wrote about this in the book.
I mean, I have a
whole chapter on it.
Chapter nine is all about that.
Yeah.
But I think I still undersold
the importance of how socially
reinforced our habits are.
Mm-hmm.
Um, and then it also references
this, uh, the importance
of a shared identity.
I think that ultimately a
shared identity is really one
of the most powerful forces
for getting habits to stick.
Mm-hmm.
You know, like if you look
at, um, if you look at it in a
big way, you can look at like
religions, you know, people,
religions are really interesting
places to look for habits.
Mm-hmm.
People get in the habit of going
to church every Sunday for.
50 years.
Yeah.
Largely because it's
reinforced the other people
in their neighborhoods go.
The people on their block, uh,
go, they see their friends there.
They, it's a very
socially reinforced habit.
Yes.
Um, same thing is
true in smaller ways.
Like let's say you move into a
new house and you walk outside
on Tuesday night and you see
all your, uh, neighbors have
their recycling bins out.
Yeah.
And you're like, huh.
People like us do things like this.
Like people who live
in this neighborhood
recycle on Tuesday nights.
Yes.
I guess we need to
sign up for recycling.
And there are really
almost an infinite range of
examples that are like that.
Both large and small.
Yeah.
Where our habits are.
We notice them because the
people around us are doing
them, which is what the Q
portion is, you referenced.
Yeah.
We desire to do them.
We crave to follow through
on them because by doing the
same, we fit in or signal to
the other people around us.
Hey, I get it.
I'm part of the tribe too.
Yeah.
Um, it becomes easier to
do it because sometimes you
have friends helping you
out, you know, like it's like
having a spotter at the gym.
Yeah.
Like, oh, people like us help
each other out when a set is hard.
Yeah.
Um, and then ultimately it
becomes satisfying because, uh,
you enjoy being praised for it.
You know, other people are
like, Hey, it was great to
see you at church on Sunday.
Yeah.
Or, you know, really good
job on that workout today.
Um, and that feels good to
be praised for fitting in.
Yeah.
And so in that way, socially
reinforced habits or, um, the
collective identity, it hits all
four stages of habit formation.
Yeah.
Um, And I, I knew that when
I was writing it, but I
don't think I gave it as much
importance as I should have.
It, it's a very powerful
driver of behavior
Justin Jackson: in the long run.
Yeah, totally.
And I think this is why cynicism
is such a toxic, uh, attitude
and you know, I'm, I guess I'm
in Gen X, I'm born in 1980.
There's a lot of cynicism in
Gen X, and then millennials also
have a little bit of this too.
And I think, um, and actually
to be honest, everybody has it.
Baby boomers have it when, you
know, if you're a 50 year old
programmer and you're, you get
hired at a startup where the
c e O is 20 years old and we
kind of default to cynicism.
And it, it, it's such a
blocker when you're like
trying to observe those norms.
Like, oh wait, like people
like us do things like this.
Cynicism allows you to go,
well, yeah, people like that.
Do stuff like that.
I.
That's good for them,
that's good for James.
Clear.
But you know, that's
not good for me.
And, uh, what I'm trying to, um,
kind of reveal from my experience
for anyone that ever watches this
or listens to this, is that you
really do need to step outside that
and at least be open to this idea
that your life could get better.
And it could just be going, okay,
well I'm gonna, I'm gonna vote
for who I'm gonna be today and I'm
gonna vote for who I'm gonna be
tomorrow and I'm gonna keep going.
The other thing in the book
that really helped me, and
I, I'm probably gonna butcher
it so you clean up after I do
it, but you show this grid.
So imagine like on this
side of your day, it's like,
okay, I make a good decision.
So it goes up and then I make
another good decision, goes up,
but then I make a bad decision.
Like I eat a tub of ice cream and.
You know, sometimes eating
the tub of ice cream is
like de debilitating.
It's like, well, I'm done.
I, I ate the tub of ice cream.
I suck at this.
I'm just gonna go get into
bed and forget about it.
And in your grid, you show,
wait, but you're still up here.
Like you can just make
another good decision and
then you're back up again.
Mm-hmm.
And I like that idea of kind
of navigating your ideas, not
being so hard on ourselves.
Did, did I kind of get that right?
James Clear: Yeah.
I, um, so this is the, I
don't know if you can see
it, but this is the image.
Oh, yeah.
Yeah.
But it's, it's, uh, It's this idea
that like the difference between
a good day and a bad day is often
just a series of choices, right?
Yeah.
And you can win each
little moment, right?
You can win each decisive moment.
Just because you ate the tub
of ice cream doesn't mean you
can't win the next moment.
Yes.
Um, and uh, and so one thing
that I was thinking about when
I wrote that is this concept
that I call decisive moments.
Um, this idea that there are
a few choices each day, maybe
somewhere between say five
and 10, that kind of determine
the next chunk of time.
And so, so for example, there's a
moment for me each morning where
I sit down and either I open up
Evernote and I start writing the
next article I'm gonna work on.
Mm-hmm.
Or I go to E S P N and I
check the latest sports news.
Yeah.
And.
What happens in the next hour is
really determined by what happens
in like the first 45 seconds.
Yes.
You know, like, do I, do I go to
Evernote or do I go to E S P N?
And uh, so that is a decisive
moment in my language.
That's like a moment that
determines if I can master those
45 seconds, then I can end up
mastering the next hour that comes
afterward almost automatically.
Yeah.
Um, same thing is true.
There's a moment each night,
like five 15 or so, my wife gets
home from work and either we
change into our workout clothes
or we like sit on the couch and
watch reruns to the office and
order Indian food or whatever.
Yeah.
And both of those nights are
good nights, but the moment
to master is do we change into
our workout clothes or not?
Yeah.
If we do that, it only
takes a few minutes.
Everything else for the next
two hours is already decided.
We'll get in the car, we'll drive
to the gym, we'll do the reps.
Like it's all, it's all pretty
much done at that point.
Yeah.
So the reason I like bringing
that up or like thinking about
that is, You start to realize
there really isn't that much
that you need to master.
Yeah.
Really you just are trying
to focus your attention
on a few key decisive
moments throughout the day.
It's kind of like applying
judo to your life.
You know?
It's like apply the pressure and
the leverage at just the right
point and then the next hour kind
of falls into place automatically.
Yeah.
Um, and so I like that because
once you realize that, once
you kind of identify those high
leverage decision points, You
can organize your day and your
environment around those things.
You know, if I know that
those 45 seconds where I'm
choosing between Evernote or
E S P N is a real key moment.
Mm-hmm.
Well, I could install freedom
and then I could block E S P N
from 8:00 AM to 10:00 AM mm-hmm.
And that takes care of that
decisive moment, and it
increases the odds that I'm
gonna open a note instead.
Yes.
Um, but anyway, so little
choices like that, that are
easier to make once you've
identified some of those
Justin Jackson: key
points of leverage.
Yeah.
And you talk about in the book,
like there's some tricks too where
you can make things automatic.
Um, like, uh, you talk about near
a, y'all buying, uh, A little
device that just shuts off his
internet every night at 10.
Yeah.
Outlet timer.
And that's what's brilliant about
that is like, it shuts it off.
Like, especially if it's in
the basement or whatever, like
you're not gonna go downstairs
and like fiddle around with it.
And then it's just, it's
just, that's what happens.
Right?
Uh, if you, like, if E S P N was
really killing you, you could just
cancel your cable subscription.
That might be a bit, but
then you would, you go to
watch e s, espn, you can't.
Right.
It's, it's done.
Um, by the way, you mentioned
this in the book too, but it's
so funny how certain people's,
uh, what, what is a trigger for
some people is not for others.
Like, PN for me is not a,
that's not a temptation at all.
James Clear: Yeah.
It doesn't even
enter your worldview.
Doesn't enter
Justin Jackson: my worldview.
But it shows you how identity
is so much a part of this.
Like, if I was hanging
out with a bunch of Oilers
fans, Every single day.
Mm-hmm.
And this happened in
the co-work office.
You know, there's a few people
and they're watching Oilers games,
you know, on, on their computers.
And I realized like, if I
wanna talk to them, I've gotta
start watching Oilers games.
Yeah.
Yeah, so people like us do
things like this and so I
started developing this habit
of watching Oilers games when
before I didn't even care.
James Clear: I think, I mean, I
think this is one of the reasons
why sports is so tribal, why
people get so emotional about it,
is that it becomes a connection
point for the relationships.
It's not even the, the
game is actually, no
one would ever say that.
'cause everybody acts like the game
is the thing that matters the most.
Yeah.
But in a weird way, it's kind of a
secondary thing, you know, really.
Like, when I think back, for me,
sports is a way for my brother
and I to connect and for us to
have something to text about and
chat about throughout the week.
Yeah.
It's a thing that, you know,
it's a reason for my dad and I
to get together in person and
to go to games and hang out and
like, it's, it's all the other
stuff that it provides that
makes it so deeply meaningful.
Yes.
Um, and then you, you know,
you end up assigning a lot of
that emotion to how the team
does on the field as well.
Yeah.
And what the score is on
the scoreboard, but Yeah.
Um, so yeah, you're, it's a
good example there on that
Justin Jackson: topic then,
and this is Cory Stone is
asking this in chat, but
there's a lot of people on
Twitter that asked us too.
Given that example that you
just gave, if your meaningful
relationships are engaging in
habits that may might not be
good for you or that you want to
change, how do you navigate that?
So if you're really feeling like,
I gotta, I gotta stop watching
sports, it's just like I get
a little bit and then I just.
Go crazy, but I still wanna have
a relationship with my brother.
Right.
Uh, this is where it gets complex,
especially if you're married
to somebody, like if your wife
is, is like your wife is at
least somewhat inclined to wanna
go to the gym, I'm guessing.
But if she was like, no,
I just wanna watch Netflix
and order Indian food,
that's all I want to do.
Yeah.
How do you start to navigate those
James Clear: things?
Yeah, those are good questions.
Um, I mean, it's really hard, uh,
because especially if it's a person
who you want to stay in your life,
you know, I think, first of all,
I just wanna say I, so I have some
things I want to add to this, but
I feel like, um, it's worth noting
that this question comes up a lot.
And I think the reason it
comes up a lot is because we
all know that actually there
isn't a good, easy answer.
Mm-hmm.
And that it's like just
a hard part of life.
You know what I mean?
Like everybody wants, it's
one of those things we want
to keep asking about in hopes
that, oh, maybe there'll be
an easy way to resolve this.
Yeah.
But I think we all know,
like, it's, it's a challenge.
Yeah.
Um, Now that said, there
are a few things you can do.
So first thing is, uh, sometimes
your friends and family want
to do something different
than how you want to change.
So like you're, you wanna
stick to a new diet, they
want to eat the old way.
Mm-hmm.
Or, um, something like that.
Yeah.
Well, uh, you want to start
doing yoga, they couldn't
care less about yoga.
They don't want to
go to class with you.
Yeah.
Um, things like that.
Well, if that's the case, then
for certain habits, you don't
have to like fire your friends
and family to be able to do that.
But what you can, what you do
need, or what can be really
useful is having like a sacred
space where that occurs.
Where, I'm not saying you need
to do this with me, but just
don't make it harder on me.
Right?
Yeah.
Just don't conflict with, so,
you know, the yoga example is an
easier one where it's like, well
you, maybe you need to go to a
yoga studio away from, uh, the
friends and family that aren't
interested and start to build
friendships with people who are,
you know, I'm not saying you need
to get rid of your old friends,
but maybe it'd be helpful to build
a couple new ones who are into
yoga so that you have like a safe
space for that habit to live.
Yeah.
Um, so that's one thing.
Uh, then there's the second
piece, which is sometimes you're
building a habit that you do
want the person to like join
you on to come along with you.
You know, you, you're working out
and you would love for your spouse
to join you at the gym mm-hmm.
Or something like that.
And, uh, everybody know like
it would be good, but they
feel maybe they feel less
comfortable there than you do.
Or maybe they feel, you know, you,
uh, were previously an athlete
and they were not, and so you feel
kind of comfortable in the gym.
You've been there before in
years past, but for them it's
like new and weird and, you
know, they feel like they're
being judged and whatever.
Mm-hmm.
If you're dealing with a case like
that, The, the thing that I try to
keep in mind, and I can tell you
from working with my own family,
um, it can be incredibly useful is
praise the good, ignore the bad.
Mm-hmm.
Um, it's very hard to do.
It's very, the, the difficult
part about it is not doing
it on an individual basis,
it's that this needs to be
the new lifestyle for you.
Mm-hmm.
So when they do the thing
that you're asking them to do.
Yeah.
Don't, basically, another
way to phrase this is don't
criticize people for doing what
you were hoping they would.
Yeah.
You know, like there are so many
times when the introverted kid
in the family will come down to
the dinner table and it's like,
oh, look who decided to join us?
And it's like, well, they
finally did the thing Yeah.
That you were hoping they would
do and engage with everybody.
Yeah.
And now they just feel like
they're getting criticized for it.
Yeah.
Or.
Um, you go to the gym and your
spouse decides to join you and
they do a few sets, and then
they feel like they're done.
Yeah.
And you say, well, that
was a pretty short workout.
And what you should should be
saying is, I think it's great
that you got in here tonight.
Right?
Yeah.
Like, you weren't feeling it, but
you were still able to make it in.
Yeah.
And.
Um, so praise the
good, ignore the bad.
Yeah.
Uh, and if you can do that in the
long run, what ends up happening
is everybody likes feeling praised.
Everybody likes feeling rewarded.
They like to, it feels satisfying
to, uh, do something that the
people who love you and who
are around you, praise you for.
Mm-hmm.
And so at first you go to the gym
and they say, Hey, I'm really proud
of you for getting in here tonight.
Good job.
Yeah.
And it doesn't seem like much.
But then after two months and
three months and 10 months of
that, you turn around a year
later, and they might never
even say it, but implicitly
what they've realized is, Damn.
Every time I go to
the gym it feels good.
They like, they compliment me.
Yeah.
And that, so now all of a sudden
you start to associate going
to the gym with feeling good.
And this is a really
long game play.
Mm-hmm.
Because it takes a while for
that to reinforce itself.
But, um, you know, same thing,
like the introverted kid at the
table sits down and they say
something that happened today.
And it's like, oh, that's awesome.
Thanks for sharing that with us.
Yeah.
You know, and like on that
individual night, that one night
at dinner doesn't count for a
lot, but if every time they speak
up, they're rewarded for it, then
all of a sudden now they have a
reason to start doing that more
in the months and years to come.
Yeah.
So it takes a while, but I
think that that's like an
effective way to gradually
nudge people in the right
Justin Jackson: direction.
Yeah.
There's someone in the chat that's
saying they need to apply that
idea to themself to avoid feeling
guilty for not doing enough.
Hm.
So instead of reinforce, oh,
you idiot, you didn't go to
the gym again, you're fatty.
You know, like that's not helpful.
Uh, there's the self-talk, it
can work with self-talk as well.
James Clear: This is why I
think, uh, small habits can be
so useful in some ways, even on
the bad days because like, let's
say you're in that situation you
just said where it's like, oh,
you know, skip the gym again.
Yeah.
Well you can still do one pushup
or one air squat or whatever before
you go do a set of 10 air squats
before you hop in bed tonight.
Mm-hmm.
And.
It is not gonna
transform your body.
But that's not really the point.
The point is to prove to yourself
that it wasn't a good day.
I didn't have the best
motivation or energy.
I had a long day at work, but I
still am not the type of person
who miss work misses workouts.
Right.
Yeah.
I still prove to myself,
I still cast a vote for
being that kind of person.
I didn't let a day go by
without doing nothing.
Yeah.
And um, that can count
for a lot in the long run.
And, uh, so sometimes small
habits are less about the outcome
they deliver and more about
the identity they reinforce.
Yeah.
Justin Jackson: And I've
actually found, um, you know,
another thing I, I try to, I'm
implementing in the new year is I
decided to quit drinking alcohol.
And right now it's
ostensibly for this goal
of hitting a revenue mark.
Once I hit the goal,
then I can have a drink.
But the deeper motivation for
me was I just realized like, It
just makes, it's a depressant.
It's like there's a bunch of
reasons that it's not good for me.
And so my, my excuse or my way of
trying it out is saying, well, I'm
going for this goal, but it's been
interesting in social situations.
'cause all of my friends still
drink and that's fine with me.
But, uh, in sometimes just sharing
the goal, oh, I'm just doing this
'cause I'm going after this thing.
And, and you talk about how goals
are sometimes helpful in setting
your direction, you know, like,
okay, I'm pointed this way now.
And, uh, sometimes sharing
that with people is helpful.
The other thing is, I think
eventually if I just keep doing
this, I just, for me to say,
well, I'm a non-drinker now.
Yeah.
And so I can still go and have,
uh, my favorite and it, it's also
nice having a thing that you like.
So my favorite non-alcoholic drink
is a, a non-alcoholic Caesar.
It's a like a bloody Mary.
And to have that drink,
it's like kind of spicy.
There's a reward there.
I also have this social
crutch that I can use in
the situation, you know?
And if somebody asks me about it, I
also have this new identity, which
is, oh, I'm a non-drinker now.
I just don't drink.
And you talked about that there's
some research behind that.
I know you've mentioned it
a lot, but it's like, um,
I'm trying to quit smoking
versus I'm a non-smoker.
Right.
Is that correct?
Correct.
Right.
Yeah.
So I think that that
can be really helpful.
Yeah.
Having,
James Clear: um, I think what
you're explaining here, the
situation that you're going
through, this experience
you're having is kind of,
it's illustrating this process
of identity change, right?
Mm-hmm.
It started with, oh, I'm just gonna
put it off for a little while,
while I'm attacking this goal.
Yeah.
But then you're casting so many
votes for like, you know what?
I haven't dragged, and like,
I'm kind of benefiting from it.
Like, maybe this is
part of my identity now.
Yeah.
Maybe I'm a non drinker.
Um, and, uh, so anyway,
yeah, I I think you're
definitely on the right
Justin Jackson: track there.
Yeah.
And actually this is a good time
to bring up two Twitter questions.
Um, Maria Alre asks, um, you
know, how do you maintain habits?
How, ask him about maintaining
habits for people with depression,
anxiety, or attention deficit.
Do you wanna try to tackle that?
James Clear: Yeah.
Um, so I've tried to be careful
about saying that Atomic
Habits is about building habits
and breaking, breaking bad
habits, building good ones.
Uh, but it's not a
book on addiction.
It's not a book on depression.
It's not a book about anxiety or
a D H D or any of these other,
um, disorders or ailments.
Mm-hmm.
Um, and I don't consider
myself an expert on addiction.
However, something
interesting has happened.
So I published the, the
book and I have had a ton of
speaking requests recently.
And so I've been doing speeches
at conferences and companies and
different events and whatever.
Yeah.
And so many times I get someone
that comes up to me afterward
or that asks a question during
q and a that talks about how
useful the book was for their son
who had a D H D or their cousin
was a meth addict, and then was
able to like start to, you know,
write the ship by employing some
of these techniques or whatever.
Yeah.
Uh, which is great.
Which is very gratifying.
I still stand by my
original statement.
I'm not an expert on addiction.
I don't want to like take a
strong stance of this stuff.
Mm-hmm.
But what I've realized is that
the principles that I lay out
in atomic habits are really
about how human behavior works.
It's about how habits are formed.
Yeah.
And whether that habit is
something extreme like an
addiction or picking your skin
or O C D or A D H D or whatever.
Um, or whether it's something
more moderate, like meditating
for three minutes a day.
Yes.
Um, the fundamentals tend to be
similar and so I'm not gonna say
that the book offers a prescription
for overcoming addictions, but
what I will say is you'd be hard
pressed to find tactics in the
book that wouldn't at least help.
Mm-hmm.
Right.
That wouldn't at least nudge
people in the right direction.
Yeah.
Um, I have heard from a few readers
who specifically have said that,
uh, they had a D H D and that
they found the book very helpful.
Mm-hmm.
Um, environment design for whatever
reason has been something that's
come up multiple times for folks
who have struggled with that.
Yeah.
So, you know, it's, I think it's
kind of like if you're the type
of person who is less likely
to just remember to do it.
Yeah.
Right.
Or like, just follow your
to-do list if that's not you.
Yeah.
Then structuring an environment
where it's easier to see the
cues of your good habits.
Less likely to see
the distractions.
Less friction between you and
the good behavior, more friction
between you and the bad ones.
Yeah.
If you place yourself in that
space, it's much more likely
that you're gonna fall through.
So, yeah.
You know, those are things
that I talk about in chapter
six and 12, but I, I think
that the book applies.
Um, but I, I don't pitch it as
like a prescription for someone
dealing with a more serious issue.
Totally.
Justin Jackson: Yeah.
And I, I would say, um, again,
I'm not an expert either, but as
someone who has been, uh, dealing
with depression the past couple
years, uh, having a professional
that you go to that deals with
this stuff all the time, like
a therapist is so helpful.
And the therapist will
be very interested if
you read James's book.
So I said to my therapist,
I'm like, you know, she
starts way back here.
And then, uh, she says,
so what's new with you?
I'm like, well, you know,
I read this book and I'm
thinking, oh, what are you
thinking about doing with that?
Oh, I'm thinking about
maybe, um, quitting alcohol.
Oh, well that's, you know,
there, there's some reinforcement
from the professionals.
Hmm.
And, uh, likewise with my, my
doctor, you know, when I, when
I had depression and I went
to my physician, she said she
gave me two prescriptions.
Um, quit drinking alcohol and quit,
uh, taking any kind of cannabis.
And the reason is she says, those
are going to make you feel bad.
Now, the trigger in
that case was my doctor.
It's nice when you have
a doctor saying, listen,
this is your prescription.
Oh, and double the amount
of exercise I was doing.
So three things, those, so I did
that for three months and then,
you know, I went back to my old
habits, but now I have that memory.
Of what it was like
for three months.
And it's been a powerful trigger
for me to, you know, when I am
starting to notice my mood go down,
I can re, I remembered, you know,
my doctor's prescription was quit
drinking, quit, you know, eating
edibles and doubling my exercise.
And that's been helpful
for me personally.
So I think if you're reading the
book, let your professional in
your life know about it is good.
One thing I want you to do is,
uh, 'cause I love the imagery,
but, uh, and this is probably
unfair to you, is to give
the ice cube example, but use
Celsius instead of Fahrenheit.
James Clear: So, um, this
is an example from the
first chapter of the book.
Um, and I actually, as a side
note, I thought about this.
I was like, man, we're gonna
have to get these changed
for the foreign editions.
Like, we're gonna,
it's gonna need to be.
But anyway, so yeah, you came.
Yeah.
The, uh, The core idea is that the
process of changing your habits
is, well, it's similar to what we
talked about early on, that there's
often this valley of death, that
there's this period where you're
just kind of building up latent
potential, but you're not really
releasing any of the results yet.
Yeah.
And I like to equate it to the
process of heating up an ice cube.
You know, so you've got,
you've got this ice cube
sitting on the table, right?
And so let's say it's like
negative three degrees in there.
Yeah.
Right?
So you're, you're a negative three.
It's cold.
You can see your breath, the
ice cube's sitting there,
you heat it up, negative
two, negative one, still,
there's this ice cube sitting
there, nothing has happened.
Yeah.
Right.
Um, then you go from negative
one to zero, and all of a sudden
you have this one degree shift.
No different than any of the other
shifts that came before it, but you
have this phase transition, right?
And like the ice
cube starts melting.
And that, I think is
indicative of what it often
feels like to change a habit.
You're making these little
improvements, you're trying to
make these 1% changes, these
one degree shifts each day.
And you're like, it's really
easy to get, um, frustrated or
even depressed at that point.
You know?
It's like, I've been running
for three weeks, how come I
can't see a change in my body?
Yeah.
You know?
Or I've been writing blog
posts for six months now.
How come this site
isn't popular yet?
Mm-hmm.
And the key point there is
your work was not being wasted.
It's just being stored.
Yeah.
Complaining about sticking to
a habit for two months or three
months, or even six months
or a year, and not having the
outcome that you want is kind
of like complaining about
heating the ice cube from
negative three to negative one
degrees and it not melting yet.
Yeah.
You know, like the, the
work was not wasted.
It's just being stored.
And I love that quote.
That's in that same section
from Jacob Reese, who it
hangs in the locker room with
the San Antonio who've won
five N B A championships.
Yeah.
And it says, essentially when I
feel like giving up, I think about
the stone cutter who continues
to hammer away at the stone a
hundred times without it splitting
and then finally on the hundred
first blow it cracks in two.
Yeah.
And I know that it wasn't
the hundred that came there.
I know it wasn't the hundred
first swing that did it, but the
hundred that came before, right?
Yes.
And like it's that same idea.
You know, the reason the site
takes off is not because of the
one viral article, it's because
of the 55 that you wrote in
the weeks and months prior.
The reason that you see a change
in your body is not because today's
workout radically transformed you.
It's because you've been sticking
to it for eight months now.
Yes.
Um, and it's really about.
Showing up, continue to put those
swings in, continue to raise
the temperature by one degree,
and eventually you hit that
phase transition where you can
see the results of your work.
Justin Jackson: Yeah.
And that image has been
so powerful in my life.
Uh, the rea, like I've been telling
people about this book, and, and
I actually notice there's kind
of like a, a coffee shop test.
Like if I hear people talking
about something from internet
culture in a coffee shop, like
real people, then something's hit
and atomic habits is like that.
Like it hit the, the, the kind
of mainstream and that image
of just raising the temperature
a little bit every day.
Now I feel like I'm, I'm a
few months into this and uh,
I'm a little bit kind of like,
uh, evangelical about it.
Like I'm saying now, I'm like, God,
like my life is so much better and
it's because of just these little
changes over time in the same
direction I can now I can see it.
Now I can see that I
feel better, you know?
Wow, man, quitting alcohol,
that was one thing.
And then wow, showing up at
the gym three or four times
a week, that really helps.
And wow.
Like reading a real book every
night before I go to bed.
All of these things keep kinda
adding up and do make a meaningful
difference in your life.
Even though way back when, when
you're starting, you feel like,
well, nothing's gonna help.
Me now.
Mm-hmm.
Uh, it's, I, I, I wanna be clear
that this, these ideas have
meaningfully impacted my life.
So I'm, yeah.
I'm really thankful you, I'm
thankful you wrote that book.
I'm thankful you, uh, you
talked to me in the airport.
It's been really great for me.
James Clear: Oh, that's awesome.
Thank you so much for sharing that.
And, uh, ultimately that's what
the whole thing is for, right?
I mean, it just, it makes it feel
like it was worth the effort to
spend a few years writing it and
working on it, so, that's great.
Justin Jackson: Yeah.
Um, so before you go, um, some
people are asking like, what
recommendations for systems,
services, tools, trackers?
I know you have a
new one coming out.
Do you wanna talk about that?
James Clear: Uh, sure.
Yeah.
So I got it right here
next to me actually.
So this is a habit journal, um,
and we, uh, we just launched it,
um, two weeks ago and it's got,
it's basically a doc grid notebook.
So if you're into bullet
journaling or you're into keeping
a notebook or use a notebook,
uh, the vast majority of it are
doc grid pages, so you'll be able
to use it like any normal one.
But then at the back there's
a section with a habit tracker
templates, and I don't know if
you can see that very well, but
I've been using it, for example,
this is this month, so you can
see me tracking my habits on here.
Um, and, uh, so anyway, those,
uh, templates are in the back
and they're also perforated,
so you can tear 'em out and
put 'em on your desk or put
'em on your kitchen counter or
your refrigerator or whatever.
Yeah.
And then, uh, and then at the very
beginning of the book, there is a
section called One Line Per Day.
So I've been using it
for what happened today.
And so I've been writing
down what happened each day.
And uh, there are 31 lines, so
one for each day of the month,
and, uh, there are 12 of 'em.
So by the time you get to the
end of the year, you should be
able to flip through and see,
you know, if you, I'm doing
what happened today, Sean Blanc.
It does, uh, what's the
highlight of the day.
Yeah.
Um, some other ones that
I've seen are, you know,
what am I grateful for?
Or you could use it as
like a productivity thing.
You could say like, what's
my most important task today?
Yeah.
Uh, things like that.
So there are a lot of examples
in the back of the Notebook
who I have like 16 pages of
examples of how to use it.
But, uh, but anyway, it's uh,
called The Habit Journal and,
um, yeah, I'm excited about it.
I think it'll be a, a good tool to
help people build better habits.
Cool.
Justin Jackson: And a lot of folks,
I've heard from a lot of folks
that really like the audiobook,
so a few folks aren't readers,
go check out the audiobook.
Uh, people like us
read Atomic Habits.
Is that, does that works?
I love it.
So thanks again for
your time James.
Really appreciate it, man.
Awesome.
James Clear: Thank you.
Justin Jackson: There you go.
Hope that was helpful for you.
Uh, like I said, I really recommend
the book, atomic habits.com.
Uh, that journal that he's talking
about is also available there,
folks, it's 2019 and if you are
tired of bootstrapping alone, I've
been running an online community,
especially for Bootstrappers
solopreneurs, indie makers,
and it's called MegaMaker Club.
Go to megamaker.co/club if
you want more information.
It's not open right now,
but you can sign up for the
waiting list, and I will
talk to you next episode.
Thanks for listening.
Podcast hosting is
provided by Transistor fm.
They host our MP three files,
generate our r s s feed, provide
us with analytics and help us
distribute the show to Spotify,
apple Podcasts and more.
If you want to start your own
podcast or you want to switch
to transistor, go to Transistor
Data fam slash Justin and
get 15% off your first year.